<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Memoires of the affairs of France during the reign of the present king Lewis the XIV. Containing the most noted exploits of the now Prince of Condé, the late Mareschal de Turenne, and all the chief commanders in the French armies. Done out of French. Licensed May the 10th, 1675. Roger L'Estrange.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 77 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89038</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1669aA</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R215401</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899675</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899675</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135098</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89038)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135098)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2431:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Memoires of the affairs of France during the reign of the present king Lewis the XIV. Containing the most noted exploits of the now Prince of Condé, the late Mareschal de Turenne, and all the chief commanders in the French armies. Done out of French. Licensed May the 10th, 1675. Roger L'Estrange.</title>
                  <author>J. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 143, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by J.C. for T. Dring, at the Harrow at the corner of Chancery-lane in Fleet-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The translator's 'Advertisement' is signed: J.W.</note>
                  <note>Translator's 'Advertisement' (A2r):  "This brief account of many great actions, translated out of the French history reduite en sommaire ...".</note>
                  <note>Original French title not traced.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Louis --  XIV, --  King of France, 1638-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIV, 1643-1715 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135098:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135098:1"/>
            <p>Memoires Of the Affairs of FRANCE, During the Reign of the preſent KING <hi>LEWIS</hi> the XIV. CONTAINING The moſt noted Exploits of the now Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> the late Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal <hi>de Turenne,</hi> and all the chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders in the French Armies. Done out of French.</p>
            <q>
               <hi>Ex pede Hercules.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <div type="license">
                        <p>Licenſed <hi>May</hi> the 10th, 1675.</p>
                        <closer>
                           <signed>Roger L'Eſtrange.</signed>
                        </closer>
                     </div>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed by <hi>J. C.</hi> for <hi>T. Dring,</hi> at the Harrow at the corner of <hi>Chancery-lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="notice">
            <pb facs="tcp:135098:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135098:2"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THis brief Account of many great Actions, Tranſlated out of the French Hiſtory <hi>reduite en Sommaire,</hi> may ſatisfie the Curious as to the Affairs of <hi>France</hi> under her active Monarch who now go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns, till a more elaborate Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory, and conſequently more cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſpondent to the Grandeur of its Subject gives a fuller and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular account to the publick</p>
            <p>'Tis poſſible, ſome may think our Author writes with too much concern and intereſt of his own party: ſuch upon due conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, will acknowledge this the beſt, or, if you had rather, the
<pb facs="tcp:135098:3"/>
moſt <hi>janté</hi> of all the defects pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to that people; and that the <hi>French</hi> are to be applauded in this particular, more than ſome of their Neighbour-Nations, that they always ſpeak the beſt of their King and Country; not ſeeking to finde fault with the Royal Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct, but to magnifie it rather more than leſs, than the true me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Actions.</p>
            <p>Hiſtorical Abbreviations, though in a ſmall Volume, are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways of the leaſt uſe: for beſide the Example of <hi>Juſtin</hi> the Epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mizer of <hi>Trogus</hi> among the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients, we have in this our Age, the judicious Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> who with much judgement and fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, has in this ſort of <hi>Miniature,</hi> drawn to the life the Tragical Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
<pb facs="tcp:135098:3"/>
of our late Soveraign, of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-Sacred Memory.</p>
            <p>There is no need of a further Preface, than onely to admoniſh the Reader that the Dates and Timing of things, ſo oft occurring in this ſhort Hiſtory, muſt be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood according to the Forrain (or new) <hi>Stile,</hi> ten days more forward than ours. Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. W.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:135098:4"/>
            <head>Some Books lately printed for <hi>T. Dring,</hi> at the Harrow at <hi>Chance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi>-lane-end in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">1. A Relation of the Conference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Will. Laud</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury</hi> and Mr. <hi>Fiſher</hi> the Jeſuite. The third Edition, in Folio. Price 8 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Syſtema Agriculturae;</hi> the myſtery of Huſbandy diſcovered: Treating of the neweſt and moſt advantagious ways of improving all ſorts of Lands, in Folio. Price 8 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Englands</hi> Eminent Danger and only Remedy: Faithfully conſidered and repreſented, in Octavo. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Ancilla Pietatis;</hi> or the Hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maid to Private Devotion. The ninth Edition, in Octavo. Price 4 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Poems upon ſeveral occaſions, in Engliſh and Latine. By <hi>John Milton;</hi> with a ſmall Tract of Education, to Mr. <hi>Hartlib,</hi> in Octavo. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. The French Cook, preſcribing the neweſt ways of Cookery. The third Edition, in Octavo. Price 2 <hi>s.</hi> 6 <hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. The Four Ages of <hi>England,</hi> or the Iron Age, with other ſelect Poems written
<pb facs="tcp:135098:4"/>
in the year 1648. in Octavo. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. The Devout Communicant exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plified, in his behaviour before, at, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Sacrament. The third Edition, much corrected, in Twelves. Price 1 <hi>s.</hi> 6<hi>d.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <head>Plays.</head>
               <item>Love and Honour.</item>
               <item>Unfortunate Lovers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thierry</hi> and <hi>Theodoret.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Woman-Hater.</item>
               <item>Changeling.</item>
               <item>Albumazar.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Plays lately Printed.</head>
               <item>Love-tricks, or the School of Complements. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hero</hi> and <hi>Leander. Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Amorous Prince, or the curious Husband. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Town-ſhifts, or the Suburb-Juſtice. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Six days Adventure, or the new <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>topia. Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dumb Lady, or the Farrier made Phyſitian. <hi>C.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Old Troop, or Monſieur <hi>Raggou. Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>The Rehearſal.</item>
               <item>Gentleman Dancing-maſter. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mamamouchi,</hi> or the Cittizen turn'd Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Fatal Jealouſie. <hi>Trag.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Morning-ramble, or the Town-humours. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Empreſs of <hi>Morocco. Trag.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Reformation. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Careleſs Lovers. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Macbeth. <hi>Trag.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Siege of <hi>Conſtantinople. Trag.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dutch Lover. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Country-wife. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Now in the Preſs.</head>
               <item>Woman turn'd Bully. <hi>Com.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:135098:5"/>☞ THere is now in the Preſs both a Latine and Engliſh Dictionary, compoſed by <hi>Tho. Hollyoke</hi> D. D. Son of <hi>Francis Hollyoke,</hi> the Learned Enlarger of <hi>Rider</hi>'s Dictionary; which ſaid Dictionary is in great part already printed in a fair large Folio, and will in a ſhort time be finiſhed and publiſhed, and will contain above 6000 words in the Engliſh, and 2000 in Latine, more than hath been in any Dictionary yet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant: Beſides, it will have the Phraſes, the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms, Habits and Ceremonies of Countries, for the better underſtanding of the Latine Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians; not only fit for School-boys, but ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and uſeful for all Students and Scholars whatſoever; and will be ſold by <hi>Tho. Dring,</hi> at the corner of <hi>Chancery-lane</hi> in <hi>Fleet-ſtreet,</hi> and others.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Goldman</hi>'s Dictionary lately printed with large Additions, in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>, and ſold by <hi>T. Dring.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 11. line 22. read <hi>Tournon.</hi> p. 19. l. 1. r. at the ſame time. p. 67. l. 19. r compoſed it. p. 71. l. 7. r. his Eminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. p. 71. l. 11. r. deceaſed. p. 79. l. 16. dele [to] p. 90. l. 13. r. diſadvantagious.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:135098:5"/>
            <head>MEMOIRES OF THE Reign of <hi>LEWIS</hi> the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> The preſent KING of <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1643" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1643.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">L</seg>Ewis</hi> 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> Eldeſt ſon of <hi>Lewis</hi> 13<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, being in the fifth year of his Age, ſucceeded to the Crown; the 65<hi rend="sup">th</hi> in number of our Kings.</p>
               <p>The King never dies in <hi>France; uno avulſo, non deficit alter.</hi> Therefore im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after the Court of Parliament had aſſembled, the King was received, accompanied with the Queen Regent his Mother, Monſeigneur the Duke of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:135098:6"/>
                  <hi>Anjou</hi> the King's Brother, Monſieur the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> his Uncle, and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur the Prince of <hi>Condé;</hi> where the Queen was declared Regent during the Kings minority, and Monſieur the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> General of all the Forces.</p>
               <p>No ſooner was the King ſeated in the Throne Royal, thereby to take poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the Crown of his Anceſtors, but he ſaw himſelf under the ſhadow of victorious Palms, brought from <hi>Rocroy</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of his Triumphant Army.</p>
               <p>On the 9 of <hi>May,</hi> the Duke of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guien</hi> having Rendezvouz'd his Troops on the Banks of the <hi>Oiſe,</hi> and the <hi>Somme,</hi> received advice, that the Enemy under the command of the Count <hi>d' I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemburg,</hi> had inveſted <hi>Rocroy</hi> the ſecond paſt: upon this intelligence he ſends immediately the Sieur <hi>Gaſſion</hi> to give ſome diverſion to their Attempts; who on his arrival, having made their chief Force draw together, took that oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to put 100 men into the Town;
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:135098:6"/>
and this Succour gave the Beſieged occaſion to retake their Out-works, which the Enemie had quitted. The 18 of <hi>May,</hi> was reſolved on to relieve the place effectually; to that end the Duke of <hi>Enguien,</hi> aſſiſted by the Mareſchal <hi>de l'Hoſpital,</hi> and the Mareſchals of the Camp, appeared with his Cavalry that day about two of the clock afternoon, and immediately on his arrival cauſed his Army to draw into Battalia. At five in the evening the Enemies Cannon began to play, and cut off many of our men; but they were ſoon anſwered by our Artillerie, which appeared as the Lightning to that Thunder which was to follow. The night coming on, by order of a Council of War, the diſpute was deferred till next morning the 19 of <hi>May.</hi> During this interval, a <hi>French</hi> Cavalier in the Enemies Army came over to ours, and gives advice to the Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> that General <hi>Beck</hi> was to arrive the next morning by 7 a clock with 1000 Horſe, and 3000 Foot, to re-inforce the Enemy: hereupon it
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:135098:7"/>
was reſolved to fight by break of day; which no ſooner appeared, but the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral having taken the Right wing of the Army, and the Mareſchal <hi>de l' Hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital.</hi> the Left; about a quarter of a League from <hi>Rocroy,</hi> they diſpoſed themſelves to do their beſt.</p>
               <p>The Enemies Army being compoſed of 25000 men, <hi>viz.</hi> 17000 Foot, and 8000 Horſe; the Infantry commanded by the Comte <hi>d' Iſemberg,</hi> and the Cavalry by the Duke <hi>d'Alberquerque,</hi> and the Comte <hi>de Fontaines</hi> Mareſchal General <hi>du Camp</hi> under <hi>Fanciſco de Mello</hi> General for the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> The French Army was 14000 Foot, and 6000 Horſe. The Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> having viſited the ſeveral Diviſions, and encouraged the Officers to perform their Duty, the Skirmiſh begins, and 1000 Muſqueteers of the Enemy are forced to give ground. On the Left, the Sieur <hi>de la Ferté-Seneterre</hi> charging the Enemy, the Combat was ſo obſtinate, that he was Wounded in ten ſeveral pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:135098:7"/>
and taken priſoner, though a while after reſcued. During this advantage, the Enemy took our Cannon; but the Mareſchal <hi>de l' Hoſpital</hi> with his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours charged and recovered them again: In this lively action he was wounded in the Arm with a Muſquet-ſhot, ſo that he was forced to leave the fight. This accident gave the Enemy ſuch advantage, that once more they took our Cannon, and uſed them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt us: but the Baron <hi>de Siron</hi> Mareſchal <hi>de Camp</hi> of the Cavalry ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a body of reſerve, rallies our men, and ſtops the Enemie's ſucceſs. In the mean while our Right wing, having routed the Cavalry, attaques the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Foot, which ſhe cuts in pieces. In fine, the Sieur <hi>Gaſſion</hi> coming up, they are all put to the Rout. We loſt there about 20 Officers, and as many Wounded. On the Enemies ſide, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide a great number of Dead of leſſer note, the Comte <hi>de Fontaines</hi> was kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and the Comte <hi>d' Iſemberg</hi> woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to death; and 6000 Priſoners, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:135098:8"/>
whom 200 Officers and 20 pieces of Cannon.</p>
               <p>From this ſignal Victory, which has inſencibly carried this Diſcourſe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond its intended Bounds, we will proceed to the Funerals of <hi>Lewis</hi> the Juſt; the preparatives for which, were made the 22 of <hi>July:</hi> the day preceding ended the<note n="*">A ſpace of forty days, during which time Prayers are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually made for the Dead.</note> 
                  <hi>Quarantaine,</hi> during all which time the Queen-Mother remained ſhut up, thereby to give place more opportunely to the ſenſible regrets for the loſs of her Spouſe. <hi>Monday</hi> was appointed for the Funeral-Ceremonies, at which did aſſiſt the Princes, Prelates, and Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Courts of Juſtice. The Kings Body was placed in the midſt of a Chappel all flaming with Lights, and the Solemn Service made at St. <hi>Denis</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> where alſo the Body was depoſited in the Vault of his Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors.</p>
               <p>The 29th of <hi>July,</hi> Madam the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs of <hi>Enguien</hi> was happily delivered
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:135098:8"/>
of a Son, who bears the Name of Duke <hi>d'Albert.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 2 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> youngeſt of the two Sons of the Duke of <hi>Vendôme,</hi> was arreſted, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoned in the <hi>Bois de Vincennes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Enguien,</hi> after the Victory at <hi>Rocroy,</hi> and the taking of <hi>Cirq,</hi> returns to <hi>Paris</hi> with the Comte <hi>de Rantzau;</hi> and on the 7th of <hi>October,</hi> the King and Queen Regent were plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to leave the <hi>Louvre,</hi> to inhabit at the <hi>Palais Royal:</hi> about which time alſo was ſent to the Abbey of St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains deſprez,</hi> one of St. <hi>Placidus</hi>'s Arms, by the great Maſter of <hi>Malta;</hi> which Relique was ſolemnly received by the Religious.</p>
               <p>The Civil troubles in <hi>England</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing, the Comte <hi>de Harcour</hi> was ſent on the part of his moſt Chriſtian Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to compoſe, if poſſible, the diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents between the King of great <hi>Britain</hi> and his Parliament; but he found the Spirits of the Diſſenters ſo little diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed that way, that he returned with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſucceſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:135098:9"/>About, the ſame time a crew of Raſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kals at <hi>Rovergüe,</hi> who took the name of<note n="*">Croquans.</note> Devourers, did raiſe a Tumult, which notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was ſoon after ſuppreſt by the Comte <hi>de Noüaille.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As our Kings have alwaies had this advantage, to give Laws to Strangers, and not to receive them; ſo alſo have they been conſtant Mediators of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord among Chriſtian Princes, and par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly of the reconciliation of the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> with his Holineſs, of which the Treaty was concluded at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> and the Articles ſigned by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Dongly</hi> Plenipotentiary for his Holineſs, and by the Cardinal <hi>Bichy</hi> Plenipotentiary on the part of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie for the Duke of <hi>Parma.</hi> In which Treaty he continued the Title enjoyed by our former Kings, of Arbiters of Chriſtian Princes. A while after, <hi>les</hi> Sieurs <hi>de Servient,</hi> and <hi>d'Avaux,</hi> Ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotentiaries for his Majeſty, parted from <hi>France</hi> to conclude the Peace, which in fine was preſently effected.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="9" facs="tcp:135098:9"/>The 21 of <hi>November,</hi> Monſieur <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoit</hi> Doctor and profeſſor at the <hi>Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonne,</hi> who for his ſingular merits had been named to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tres,</hi> was conſecrated at <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Mareſchal <hi>de Guebriant,</hi> a <hi>Breton,</hi> whoſe valour was ſignalized in the laſt King's Raign, being now at the ſiege of <hi>Rothweil</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> was wounded with a Faulcon-ſhot the 24th of <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> of which he died; his Body being conveyed to <hi>Paris,</hi> by the King's expreſs order, his Funerals were per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with great ſolemnity.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1644" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1644.</head>
               <p>The Year 1644. was no leſs fertile in producing new Lawrels for <hi>France</hi> than the former. But before we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to diſplay theſe Victories, it is not impertinent to obſerve, by the by, the Death of <hi>Anne de Montaſie,</hi> Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Bourbon</hi> Comte of <hi>Soiſſons,</hi> Prince of the Blood, and great Maſter of <hi>France,</hi> who died at
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:135098:10"/>
                  <hi>Paris,</hi> aged 67 years: ſhe left by her Will, 100000 Crowns to the Cheva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier <hi>de Soiſſons,</hi> Baſtard-ſon to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Comte <hi>de Soiſſons,</hi> who was ſlain in the Battle of <hi>Sedan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Town of <hi>Gravelines</hi> was beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by Monſieur the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> who inveſted it the 6. of <hi>June,</hi> aſſiſted by the Dukes of <hi>Guiſe</hi> and <hi>Nemours,</hi> the Comte <hi>de Harcour</hi> Eldeſt ſon of the Duke <hi>d'Elbeuf,</hi> and the Mareſchals <hi>de la Meleraye, de Gaſſion, de Coſſé,</hi> and the Marqueſs <hi>d'Alegre.</hi> This Siege may be placed in the number of the moſt diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, ſuch was the ſtout reſiſtance of the beſieged; which notwithſtanding had no power to ſtop the Victories of <hi>France.</hi> Here in one of our Attaques fell the Marqueſs <hi>de Nangis.</hi> In fine, the Beſieged under the Conduct of <hi>Ferdinando de Solis,</hi> finding himſelf out of all hope of Relief, which <hi>Pico<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomini</hi> had once made a ſhew of giving, ſurrendered to the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> the 29th of <hi>July.</hi> And at the ſame time died <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> 8th, after he had poſſeſs'd the Holy Seat 21 years.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:135098:10"/>Now alſo paſt an Arreſt in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament of <hi>Paris,</hi> prohibiting all Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians whatſoever, except thoſe of the Univerſity of <hi>Paris,</hi> to adminiſter in that City.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Germany,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> deſiring to relieve <hi>Friburg,</hi> beſieged in <hi>Auguſt</hi> by the Enemy, had no ſooner begun his March on this deſigne, but he underſtood of the Surrender: this news inflamed his courage to ſuch a degree, that he reſolved to recompence the loſs of the Town by a Fight; in which he ſucceeded, remaining Maſter of the field, though not without conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able loſs on our ſide. In purſuit of this Victory he beſieges <hi>Philipsburg</hi> the 24 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> which a little before we had loſt, and in leſs than 3 Weeks forceth <hi>Gaſper de Bamberg</hi> the Governour to ſurrender. We loſt there the Comte <hi>de Journon</hi> Governour of <hi>Dauphiné,</hi> and the Marqueſs of <hi>Pluvaud,</hi> with 70 Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers. <hi>Spire</hi> at the ſame time ſubmitted to the King's obedience, and received a Garriſon of French.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:135098:11"/>Amidſt theſe ſerious relations, let us mingle ſomething of ſport, though in truth it was ended with a ſad Cataſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe. A Citizen of <hi>Paris</hi> named <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tou,</hi> being at <hi>Vitry,</hi> a Town two Leagues from <hi>Paris,</hi> with ſeveral other jovial Companions, undertook to preſent a Comedy, where <hi>Bertou</hi> ſhould perſonate a Dead man; who according to the deſigne of the Play, was to be raiſed to life by the Inchantments of a certain Magician: But being toucht with the Magicians Wand to that purpoſe, he was found without motion. Never did Actor repreſent a dead man's part more truely, for indeed he was dead. Which Accident gave matter for ſerious conſideration to all the company.</p>
               <p>The 6 of <hi>October, Elizabeth</hi> Queen of <hi>Spain,</hi> Aunt to our King <hi>Lewis</hi> 14, dies at <hi>Madrid,</hi> in the 42 year of her age, leaving two ſons to <hi>Philip</hi> 4th, King of <hi>Spain,</hi> her Spouſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1645" type="year">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:135098:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1645.</head>
               <p>In the Moneth of <hi>February,</hi> the year 1645. begun with a horrid Tempeſt, accompanied with ſuch an Earthquake at <hi>Poictiers,</hi> as proved the ruine of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral houſes, and the more elevated parts of ſome Churches.</p>
               <p>A few daies after this, died at <hi>Paris,</hi> in the Abbey of St. <hi>Geneviefve,</hi> Meſſire <hi>Francois de la Rochefaucault,</hi> aged 87 years, and Cardinal ſince the year 1607. His Life was a model of Sanctity, and that by the teſtimony of the moſt ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous perſons of his age. The Pope himſelf, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> 8th, who having granted him ſomething which he deſired, gave him beſides this Elogie: <hi>Behold here all that remains of Sanctity, Piety, and Truth, in our Apoſtolick Colledge.</hi> Long time before his Death he Regulated the Abbey of St. <hi>Geneviefve</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> to which Father <hi>Fore,</hi> deceaſed not long before him, was elected; which courſe is ſtill obſerved in the promotion of the Abbot, the place being Triennial.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:135098:12"/>A while after this, the Comte <hi>de Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour</hi> departed hence, to execute his charge of Vice-Roy in <hi>Catalonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean time the Comte <hi>du Pleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſis-Praſlin</hi> lays ſiege to the Town of <hi>Roſe</hi> in the County of <hi>Rouſſilon,</hi> with 8000 Foot and 2000 Horſe: Thoſe of our party that lay on that ſide of the Town next the Sea, were ſurprized with ſuch an impetuous and ſudden ſtorm, that the Gallies of the Sieur <hi>de</hi> St. <hi>Juſt,</hi> and the Sieur <hi>de Birades,</hi> were daſht to pieces; the Officers leapt into the Sea, to ſave themſelves by ſwimming: This notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding was no impediment to the progreſs of the Siege.</p>
               <p>Not long after was celebrated the Nuptials of Madamoiſelle <hi>de Rohan</hi> ſole Heireſs to the deceaſed Monſieur the Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> with Monſieur <hi>de Chabot</hi> of the houſe of <hi>Chabots</hi> or <hi>Jarnac</hi> in <hi>Angoumois,</hi> youngeſt ſon to the Governour of <hi>Leucate:</hi> this gave occaſion to her Mother, who could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be wrought to conſent to this Match, to publiſh that ſhe was not ſole Heireſs
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:135098:12"/>
(though ſhe had formerly declared it by a publick Inſtrument, when a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage was treated for her Daughter with Monſieur the Comte of <hi>Soiſſons.</hi>) To this purpoſe ſhe produces an Infant about 15 years old, baptized at <hi>Paris</hi> in the Church of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> by the Name of <hi>Tancrede,</hi> which ſhe maintained to be ſon to the late Duke of <hi>Rohan;</hi> and that ſhe had always kept him concealed, fearing he might be taken from her, while Monſieur the Duke of <hi>Rohan</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired himſelf at <hi>Venice;</hi> that he had been nurſed in <hi>Normandy,</hi> in the houſe of the father of her Maiſtre <hi>de Hostel,</hi> and after that tranſported into <hi>Holland.</hi> Upon this Caſe did afterwards ariſe that famous Pleading in the Parliament at <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Germany,</hi> the Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne</hi> was defeated by <hi>Jean de Wert,</hi> who commanded the Army of <hi>Bavarians,</hi> near to <hi>Mariandal,</hi> the 5 of <hi>May.</hi> The Colonels <hi>Roſe,</hi> the Vicomte <hi>de Lamed,</hi> and the Sieur <hi>Paſſage,</hi> Priſoners of War, were carried to <hi>Ingolſtat.</hi> The miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune of this Battle was recompenſed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:135098:13"/>
in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> the Comte <hi>du Pleſſis-Praſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin</hi> having taken the Town of <hi>Roſe,</hi> which the Spaniards ſurrendered upon honourable Compoſitions the 28th of <hi>May.</hi> After this <hi>la Motte</hi> in <hi>Lorain,</hi> which Garriſon did much damage upon our Frontiers, was ſurrendered to the Marquiſs <hi>de Villeroy</hi> the firſt of <hi>July,</hi> by <hi>Clicot</hi> Governour of the place, who was forced to capitulate after a long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance. The 11 of the ſame moneth the Fort of <hi>Mardike</hi> ſubmitted to Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur the Duke of <hi>Orleans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the ſame time <hi>Mary de Jars,</hi> called <hi>la</hi> Damoiſelle <hi>de Gournay,</hi> Kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman to the Sieur <hi>Montagne</hi> (from whoſe Pen we have the Book of <hi>Eſſays</hi>) being aged 80 years, died at <hi>Paris.</hi> She ſurpaſt all her Sex in Learning, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving left behind her ſeveral Printed works: many great perſons did honour her, among whom <hi>Juſtus Lipſius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 6 of <hi>July,</hi> Meſſire <hi>Joſias de Rant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zau,</hi> deſcended of the Illuſtrious houſe of the Comtes <hi>de Rantzau</hi> in <hi>Holſtein,</hi> whom the courſe of our Hiſtory has
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:135098:13"/>
ſhewn in many generous Actions for the Service of <hi>France,</hi> received the Staff of Mareſchal from the hand of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> by the King's order. He had loſt in ſeveral Encounters one Eye, one Arm, and one Leg; which notwithſtanding had no ways diminiſht the vivacity of his Spirit, and that as well in a Council of War, as in a brave reſolution in Engagements.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> continuing ſtill the progreſs of his Arms, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching up into <hi>Germany,</hi> gave Battle neer <hi>Nordlinguen</hi> the 3 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> where the Imperialiſts were defeated, Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Mercy</hi> ſlain, with 4000 Enemies, and about 2000 taken Priſoners, among whom General <hi>Gleen.</hi> After this he takes <hi>Nordlinguen,</hi> which ſubmitted to diſcretion. We loſt there the Marqueſs <hi>de Piſani,</hi> ſon to the Marqueſs <hi>de Rom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boüillet,</hi> and the Sieurs <hi>de Gremonville</hi> and <hi>Marſon;</hi> beſide the Mareſchal <hi>de Grammont,</hi> who remained Priſoner, with the Marqueſs <hi>de la Chaſtre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Town of <hi>Bourburg</hi> neer <hi>Grave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:135098:14"/>
ſometime part of the Appenage of the houſe of <hi>Vendôme,</hi> but of late U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped by the <hi>Spaniard,</hi> being beſieged by Monſieur the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendered the 19th of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> 600 men went out of it, who were conducted to <hi>Gravelines</hi> as Priſoners of War. And the 21 of the ſame Moneth was taken <hi>Mont-Caſſel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereupon <hi>Bethune,</hi> a conſiderable place in <hi>Artois,</hi> ſurrendered by Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition to the King's Army: and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after, the Mareſchal <hi>de Rantzau</hi> inveſts the Town of <hi>Lilers,</hi> and the Mareſchal <hi>de Gaſſion</hi> that of St. <hi>Venant;</hi> both which ſurrendered not long after, and thereby made us Maſters of the River <hi>Lis.</hi> In the mean time the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> went to take an exact view of the Town of <hi>Armentiers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not long after this, the Sieur <hi>Maze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin,</hi> of the Order of St. <hi>Dominique,</hi> Maſter of the Holy Palace, and at preſent Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Aix,</hi> departed from <hi>Rome</hi> for <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 7 of <hi>September,</hi> the King went
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:135098:14"/>
to the Parliament. At the ſame hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened a difference in the Convent of Reformed <hi>Jacobins,</hi> in the new ſtreet St <hi>Honoré,</hi> between the <hi>Pariſians</hi> and <hi>Gaſcons</hi> of this Reformation: theſe demanding to be ſeparated from the other. The affair was urged to ſuch a point, that the Queen Regent gave order to the Chancellor, with certain Biſhops and Councellors of State, to compoſe it: who ordained, that there ſhould be no ſeparation; that none of the <hi>Pariſians</hi> might be ſent into <hi>Gaſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie;</hi> and that there ſhould be but 8 <hi>Gaſcons</hi> in the ſaid Monaſtery; four of which to be of the Province of St. <hi>Maximin,</hi> and the other four of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Town of <hi>Armentiers,</hi> through which paſſes the River <hi>Lis,</hi> and in which are about 6000 Inhabitants, ſurrender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Compoſition to the Mareſchals <hi>de Gaſſion</hi> and <hi>de Rantzau,</hi> on the 10 of <hi>December.</hi> In the mean while, by the mediation of the moſt Chriſtian King, a Peace was concluded between
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:135098:15"/>
the Kings of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Denmark;</hi> the Sieur <hi>de la Tuillerie</hi> being ſent Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador Extraordinary on the part of his Majeſtie.</p>
               <p>The 20th of <hi>September,</hi> was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded at the Caſtle of <hi>Fontainbleau</hi> the Contract of Marriage between <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ladiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and <hi>Lowiſa-Maria de Gonzague,</hi> Daughter to the Duke of <hi>Mantua,</hi> and Aunt to him now living. The Contract, among other things, contained, that the Princeſs <hi>Mary</hi> ſhould have in the name of Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y two Millions and one hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and Livres of French money; of which ſum, the moſt Chriſtian King ſhould pay ſix hundred thouſand Livres in free gift; and for the other fifteen hundred thouſand Livres, was to be valued her Title which ſhe might have to ſucceed her Father in the Dutchy of <hi>Mantua.</hi> The King Authorized this affair as her Father, and the Queen Regent as her Mother, who thereupon did ſigne the Contract.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Sunday</hi> the 29th of <hi>October,</hi> the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:135098:15"/>
Embaſſadors of <hi>Poland</hi> made their magnificent entry into <hi>Paris,</hi> at the Gate of St. <hi>Anthony.</hi> The pomp was ſo full of admiration to the eyes of all Spectators, (who fill'd the High-ways for the ſpace of two Leagues from <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi>) inſomuch that ſeveral Authors have in their Writings left us very am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple deſcriptions of it. I ſhall therefore dwell no longer on this particular of ſmall conſequence, having ſo large a Subject of the Exploits of War, and our Generals of Armies. Let it ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice that the Embaſſadors were the Biſhop of <hi>Varuic,</hi> and the Palatine of <hi>Poſnanie,</hi> who the <hi>Tueſday</hi> following had Audience of their Majeſties, and afterwards of the Princeſs, the deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Queen of <hi>Poland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>During theſe Secular Grandeurs, the Church Triumph'd in three Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions: One was of Prince <hi>Edward</hi> Count Palatine of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> Huſband to the Princeſs <hi>Anne de Gonzague</hi> Siſter to the Queen of <hi>Poland,</hi> who abjured Hereſie between the hands of Father
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:135098:16"/>
                  <hi>Fore</hi> a <hi>Cordelier,</hi> the 3d of <hi>November.</hi> This was immediately preceded by that of the Marqueſs <hi>de Montauſier,</hi> who was made Governour of <hi>Angoumois</hi> and <hi>Xaintonge.</hi> Afterwards, in the moneth of <hi>July,</hi> at the ſiege of <hi>Bourburg,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed that of the Comte <hi>de Rantzau,</hi> who (as may be ſeen in the courſe of this Hiſtory) after many Exploits of War, and in divers Combats, having left himſelf but half a Body, had not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding a Soul remaining ſo ſound and entire, as to diſpoſe himſelf into the Boſom of the Church; in which affair alſo was employed Father <hi>Fore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the 20th of <hi>October,</hi> the Town of <hi>Balaguier</hi> ſubmitted to the Comte <hi>de Harcour</hi> Vice-Roy in <hi>Catalonia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 3d of <hi>September</hi> happened a great fire in the Town of <hi>Angers,</hi> which begun in the houſe of a certain Paſtry-Cook; the Flame raged with ſuch vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence, that it did much damage to many Houſes: this occaſioned the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe of many people to aſſiſt. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Buſtle, ſomebody adviſed to
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:135098:16"/>
caſt into the midſt of the Flames cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain little Scappularies of the Virgin of Mount <hi>Carmel;</hi> with which action the fire was appeaſed and extinguiſh'd, yet the Scappularies themſelves no ways indamaged.</p>
               <p>During this, they murmur at <hi>Rome</hi> to ſee the Arms of <hi>France</hi> placed over the Palace-gates of Cardinal <hi>Barberin,</hi> and <hi>Dom Thadaeo</hi> his Brother Prefect of the City: But the Cardinal <hi>Barberin</hi> gave an account of the action to his Holineſs.</p>
               <p>On the 5th of <hi>November,</hi> the Queen of <hi>Poland</hi> was eſpouſed to the Prince Palatine of <hi>Poſnanie,</hi> repreſenting the perſon of the King his Maſter. The Ceremonies were performed at the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace Royal</hi> by the Biſhop of <hi>Varuic,</hi> with permiſſion of the Cardinal of <hi>Lions</hi> Grand <hi>Aumoſnier</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Paris:</hi> And after Maſs, was celebrated the Feaſt Royal.</p>
               <p>And now the Mareſchal <hi>de Gaſſion,</hi> who commands the King's Army in the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> cuts in pieces the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:135098:17"/>
Forces, takes 19 Enſignes, and 8 Cornets of Horſe, and 4000 Priſoners. At the ſame time the French Army, under the conduct of the Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne,</hi> takes <hi>Treves</hi> by Compoſition, of which place the Comte <hi>de Laverne</hi> was Governour. Afterwards the Arch-Biſhop Elector of the Empire was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to his poſſeſſion.</p>
               <p>This year the Aſſembly of the Clergy was held at the great <hi>Auguſtins</hi> in <hi>Paris.</hi> And at the ſame time was finiſh'd that painful Work, the great Bible, which contains ſeven ſeveral Texts, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> the <hi>Samaritan,</hi> the <hi>Chaldee,</hi> the Seventy, the <hi>Syriack,</hi> St. <hi>Jerom</hi>'s Tranſlation, and the <hi>Arabick:</hi> The Work conſiſts of ten Volumes, and was perfected at the expence of the Sieur <hi>le Jay.</hi> This admirable Piece being now compleated, was preſented to the King and Qu. Regent, in the preſence of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> Monſieur the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> Monſieur the Cardinal of <hi>Mazarine,</hi> and Monſieur the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor. <hi>Le</hi> Sieur <hi>le Jay</hi> received for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:135098:17"/>
recompence a <hi>Brieve</hi> to be Councellor of State, and 2000 Livres of Penſion.</p>
               <p>The 27th of <hi>November, Loüiſe-Marie de Gonzague</hi> Queen of <hi>Poland,</hi> parted from <hi>Paris</hi> to finde the King her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, with the Embaſſadors: the King and Queen Regent accompanied her almoſt to St. <hi>Denis</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and bid her adieu before the Chappel of <hi>Clig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancourt,</hi> leaving with her the Sieurs <hi>de Rhodes</hi> and <hi>Sanctot,</hi> great Maſters of the Ceremonies, the Sieurs <hi>de Berliſe</hi> Conductor of Embaſſadors, and <hi>de Linage</hi> Captain-Enſigne to the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Guards, to conduct her to the Frontiers; and to cauſe the ſame honour to be paid her in all places where ſhe paſt, as to the King and Queens own perſons. Having remained two days at St. <hi>Denis,</hi> ſhe paſt on to <hi>Senlis, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peigne, Noyon,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronne,</hi> where ſhe was received by the Sieur <hi>d'Hoquincourt</hi> the Governour. Paſſing ſtill further, ſhe reſted in the middle of a Field, where the Sieurs <hi>de Rhodes, Sanctot, Berlize,</hi> and <hi>Linage</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:135098:18"/>
took their leave of her, having firſt delivered her into the hands of the Comte <hi>de Buquoy</hi> General of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Army. Hereupon a ſuſpenſion of Arms was made for three days. In the mean time the Sieur <hi>de Hoquincourt</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be erected a Table, for the enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment of 80 perſons. Neer at hand ſtood ſix <note n="*">
                     <hi>Muid,</hi> in French, <hi>3</hi> of which make a Tun.</note> Hogſheads of Wine with their heads knockt out. The King of <hi>France</hi>'s Health was begun by the Governour of <hi>Cambray;</hi> the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s by the Sieur <hi>d'Hoquincourt:</hi> and in like manner the Combat of the Glaſs continued till the Queens depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; at which time the <hi>Comte de Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quoy</hi> preſented her with a Company of 100 <hi>Spaniards</hi> for her Guard.</p>
               <p>On the 4th of <hi>December,</hi> the Fort <hi>Mardike,</hi> which the French had took like Lyons, the Spaniards ſurprized like Foxes.</p>
               <p>When the Queen of <hi>Poland</hi> paſs'd through the Country of <hi>Cologne,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trec,</hi> there was preſented to her
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:135098:18"/>
ſight a Damſel, named <hi>Anne Marie de Skurman,</hi> a Virgin indowed with many handſome qualities; ſhe underſtood and ſpoke divers Languages, as the <hi>Arabic, Turkiſh, Greek, French,</hi> and <hi>Spaniſh;</hi> but above all <hi>Latine,</hi> in which ſhe would anſwer to certain queſtions of Divinity and Philoſophie, in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Queen and Embaſſadors of <hi>Poland.</hi> Among ſeveral other Works, ſhe has writ two Latine Epiſtles, Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated into<note n="*">By Monſieur <hi>Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tet,</hi> one of the Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy.</note> 
                  <hi>French;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides two other which ſhe writ full of Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, in our Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, to the Queen, and to Monſieur the Cardinal of <hi>Richlieu,</hi> who thought it not below them to anſwer her in the year 1638. This Damſel is accounted one of the Wonders of the Age.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1646" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1646.</head>
               <p>The 6th of <hi>February,</hi> in the year 1646. Cardinal <hi>Francis Barberin, Dom Thadaeo</hi> his Brother Prefect of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:135098:19"/>
with four of his Children, and all their Train, arrived in <hi>Provence,</hi> having left <hi>Rome</hi> upon jealouſie ariſing from cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ill actions on the part of their Enemies. Cardinal <hi>Antonio</hi> their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther came hither the moneth before.</p>
               <p>In <hi>February,</hi> Cardinal <hi>d'Eſt</hi> Brother to the Duke of <hi>Modenae,</hi> was declared Protector of <hi>France</hi> in the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> whereupon the <hi>Breve</hi> was car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried him by Monſieur the Abbot of St. <hi>Nicholas les Angers,</hi> who at the ſame time parted from <hi>Paris</hi> for <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 14th of <hi>March,</hi> upon a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence happening between the Religious <hi>de la Mercy</hi> and their Prior, whom they refuſed to obey becauſe he was a <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con;</hi> it was Ordered by ſolemn Arreſt, that the <hi>Gaſcon</hi> ſhould remain Prior, in regard the <hi>Gaſcons</hi> are French-men as well as the Inhabitants of the other parts of the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The 21th of <hi>February,</hi> deceaſed at <hi>Paris</hi> M. <hi>Thomas de Gauffre</hi> Prieſt, heretofore Maſter of the Chamber of Accounts, who ſucceeded in the pious
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:135098:19"/>
Offices of Father <hi>Claude Bernard,</hi> in viſiting the Priſoners, and aſſiſting the Poor and Criminals at their Execution. His Body was buried at <hi>la Charité. Le Sieur Juif,</hi> Son of that famous Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rurgeon not long ſince deceaſed, ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded him in thoſe charitable Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>The diſpleaſure which the Dutcheſs Dowager of <hi>Rohan</hi> had conceived at the Marriage of her Daughter <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guerite de Rohan</hi> with Meſſire <hi>Henry de Chabot,</hi> now Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> was grown to that height, that it occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned an Arreſt in the Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Paris,</hi> which was given at this time againſt Mr. <hi>Jacob Jolly</hi> Proctor of the ſaid Court, Tutor in the Cauſe of one called <hi>Tancrede.</hi> The Arreſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibited to the ſaid <hi>Tancrede</hi> to call himſelf Son of the deceaſed Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> or to take to himſelf the Name and Arms of the Houſe of <hi>Rohan;</hi> and to the Dutcheſs Dowager and all others to give him that quality, under the penalties in the ſaid Ordinance contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:135098:20"/>
and laſtly, the ſaid parties were condemned in the coſts of Suit. This was after <hi>Martinet,</hi> the Advocate, had pleaded with no leſs Learning than E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loquence for the Lady <hi>Marguerite</hi> Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs and ſole Heireſs of <hi>Rohan,</hi> and <hi>Gaultire</hi> for <hi>Henry de Chabot</hi> Duke of <hi>Rohan:</hi> neither <hi>Jacob</hi> the Proctor, nor any other appearing for <hi>Tancrede.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the moneth of <hi>April</hi> were pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd certain Apologies in defence of the Cardinals <hi>Barberin,</hi> who had refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged themſelves in <hi>France,</hi> and put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the King's protection.</p>
               <p>Before we paſs any further, let us deliver the Queen of <hi>Poland</hi> into the hands of the King her Huſband: ſhe arrived at <hi>Warſow</hi> the 10th of <hi>March;</hi> the Prince <hi>Charles</hi> Brother to the King met her: ſhe was preſented to the King by the <hi>Comte de Bregy,</hi> in the name of both their moſt Chriſtian Majeſties. The Mareſchal <hi>de Guebriant</hi> alſo made ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Complement; but the Queen offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to kneel, as is cuſtomary to Queens when firſt they ſee their Huſbands,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:135098:20"/>
the King raiſed her with a kiſs and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace. Preſently after this, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick <hi>Nuntio,</hi> in his Pontificial habit, confirmed the Marriage with the uſual Benediction.</p>
               <p>On the 7th of <hi>May,</hi> the Cardinal <hi>Barberin</hi> went to the Aſſembly of the Clergy by way of viſit, where he was harangued by the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the ſame Moneth of <hi>May, Meſſire Philip Coſpean</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lizieux,</hi> and formerly of <hi>Nantes,</hi> a Prelate of great Piety and Learning, deceaſed in his own Dioceſs, and in the 78 year of his age.</p>
               <p>On the 7th of <hi>May,</hi> the King made his firſt Voyage out of the Territory of <hi>Paris,</hi> for <hi>Amiens,</hi> where he was received with extraordinary joy.</p>
               <p>At this time was decided by Arreſt of the Parliament at <hi>Paris,</hi> the Proceſs formerly commenced, touching the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terment of Secular perſons in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Houſes, between <hi>Nicholas Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure</hi> Doctor of Divinity of the Faculty
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:135098:21"/>
of <hi>Paris,</hi> Curate of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> and the Religious <hi>Minimes</hi> of the <hi>Place Royal;</hi> in which all the Curates of <hi>Paris</hi> joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> and all the other Religious with the <hi>Minimes.</hi> The Arreſt contain'd, that always and as often as any particular perſon ſhould chuſe his Sepulture in the Church be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to any Religious Men, or Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Women, whether without or within the Pariſh of the Defunct, the Curate or his Vicar, with all his Clergy, ſhould conduct the Corps to the Church-door of the ſaid Monaſtery, where it ſhall be received by the Superiour of the place, or ſome other of the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious to that Office appointed: after this, the Curate or Vicar having certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that the Defunct died in the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Church, he ſhall depart with his Clergy. The Lights and Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſerving at the ſaid Funeral, to be equaly divided, one moity to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and the other to the Religious. Prohibiting all Religious whatſoever to fetch and convey the Body of any De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>funct
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:135098:21"/>
deſiring to be buried in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpective Churches, unleſs in caſe of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſal by the Curates or their Vicars; being firſt duely acquainted therewith, and required to perform the ſaid Office. All this notwithſtanding not to preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice any agreements formerly made be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween any Curates, and Religious Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, touching Interments: the tenours of all which are to be duely obſerved and kept.</p>
               <p>In <hi>England,</hi> during this <hi>May,</hi> the King left <hi>Oxford</hi> in diſguiſe, being there Beſieged by the Parliament-Forces, and fled to the <hi>Scots,</hi> who ſhewed him no part of that due reception which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to their King, but ſent him under a ſtrong Convoy to <hi>Newcaſtle;</hi> to which place alſo the King of <hi>France</hi> ſends the Sieur <hi>de Montreüil</hi> to reſide neer him, and reconcile him to the Parliament.</p>
               <p>On the 9th of <hi>May,</hi> the <hi>Comte de Harcour</hi> lays ſiege to <hi>Lerida,</hi> where in our firſt Attaques we loſt the <hi>Comte de Chabot,</hi> and the Marquiſs <hi>de Gévres,</hi> Sons to the <hi>Comte de Tremes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:135098:22"/>On the 14th of <hi>June,</hi> the Town of <hi>Courtray</hi> in <hi>Flanders</hi> was taken by the French Army, notwithſtanding that Duke <hi>Charles, Picolomini,</hi> and <hi>Lamboy</hi> made a ſhew of Relief.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Italy,</hi> the Town <hi>Orbitello</hi> in <hi>Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cany</hi> was beſieged by the Prince <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas.</hi> Here our Admiral Commanding a Fleet on the part of the Beſiegers, was killed by a Cannon-ſhot in a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val fight. In fine, Prince <hi>Thomas</hi> was forced to retire, the Enemies Forces being augmented by freſh ſuccours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>July</hi> 8th, the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> Eldeſt ſon to the King of <hi>England</hi> arrived at <hi>Caën</hi> in <hi>Normandy,</hi> and from thence directly to the Queen his Mother at St. <hi>Germain en Laye.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 13th of <hi>July,</hi> died Meſſire <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger de Bellegarde</hi> Duke and Pair of <hi>France</hi> and Grand Eſcuyer, aged 83 years and 7 moneths: and the 26th of the ſame moneth died alſo his Brother <hi>Octavius de Bellegarde</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Sens.</hi> His deceaſe was preceded by two other Prelates, <hi>viz.</hi> Meſſire <hi>Abra de
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:135098:22"/>
Raconis</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Lavaur</hi> in <hi>Langue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doc,</hi> and Meſſire <hi>François de Pericard</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Eureux.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Longuvy,</hi> the onely place that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the Duke of <hi>Lorain</hi>'s Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories, was taken about this time by the Marquiſs <hi>de la Ferté Seneterre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Aſſembly of the Clergy ending about the 30th of <hi>July,</hi> Meſſire <hi>Jean François Paul de Gondy,</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Corinth,</hi> and Coadjutor in the Arch-biſhoprick of <hi>Paris,</hi> made an Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rangue to the King in the name of all the Clergy.</p>
               <p>And now Meſſire <hi>le Preſident Believre</hi> was ſent Embaſſador into <hi>England,</hi> where he had favourable Audience by the Parliament at <hi>London</hi> the 27 of <hi>July,</hi> and the firſt of <hi>Auguſt</hi> by the King at <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the beginning of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Fort of <hi>Mardike</hi> was Beſieged by Monſieur the Duke of <hi>Orleans:</hi> the brisk At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taques which we gave, took from us at the very firſt the <hi>Chivalier de la Füeillade, le Sieur du Terrail,</hi> of the ſame
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:135098:23"/>
Race with Captain <hi>Bayard;</hi> and three days after, the <hi>Comte de Fley,</hi> and the <hi>Chevalier de Fieſque.</hi> The Duke of <hi>Nemours</hi> was Wounded by a Muſquet-ſhot in his Leg, but without hurting the Bone; and as favourably, the Prince <hi>de Marſillac</hi> Eldeſt ſon to the Duke <hi>de la Rochfoucault.</hi> The 22 of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Sieur <hi>de Grignan</hi> had his Head ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off by a Cannon-ſhot. This re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance by the Beſieged enflamed the Courage of our party; and the mouth of the Channel being ſtopt by ſix ſhips of <hi>Holland,</hi> ſo that the Beſieged were forced to receive all their Relief from <hi>Gravelines,</hi> to which they had been as a Bulwork: <hi>Mardike</hi> finding her ſelf ſo ſeverely preſt, began to Parley: the Beſieged were received to Compoſition by Monſieur the Duke of <hi>Orleans;</hi> and the chief Articles were, that 3000 men, then and there in Garriſon, ſhould come out, Life and Baggage ſafe, but ſhould remain Priſoners of War. The place thus taken, the Sieur <hi>de Chalen</hi> was made Governour.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:135098:23"/>The 6th of <hi>September,</hi> the <hi>Comte Magnus Gabriel de la Gardie,</hi> Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor extraordinary from <hi>Swedeland,</hi> arrived at <hi>Paris,</hi> where he was extream kindely received by their Majeſties, and lodged at the <hi>Hoſtel de Vendôme.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the mean while News arrives at Court, that on the 17th of <hi>September,</hi> his Holineſs at the Kings Inſtance had reſtored thoſe of the Houſe of <hi>Barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rins</hi> to their Goods, conditionally, that the two Cardinals ſhould abide ſome while at <hi>Avignon.</hi> At the ſame time the Mareſchal <hi>de Baſſompierre,</hi> aged 68 years, dies ſuddainly at <hi>Provins.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dunkirk,</hi> which hitherto had been the receptacle of Pirates, who had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually ſcowred the Seas on all the Coaſts of <hi>France,</hi> was Inveſted by the Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> on the 17th of <hi>Sep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tember,</hi> and aſſaulted ſo vigorouſly by our Souldiers excited by the courage of their Commander, that on the tenth of <hi>October</hi> it ſurrendered by Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition: The Marquiſs <hi>de Leide</hi> the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour march'd out with 1500 men,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:135098:24"/>
of which 400 Sick and Wounded; and he confeſt to have loſt 600 of his beſt Souldiers. The Mareſchal of <hi>Rantzau</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to the place of Governour for the French. <hi>Dunkirk</hi> was firſt built 600 years ſince by <hi>Baudoüin</hi> Earl of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders.</hi> After that, it was burnt down by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> in the year 1388. Rebuilt by the <hi>French,</hi> and after taken by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> who kept it till the preſent Conqueſt.</p>
               <p>The King's Army in <hi>Italy,</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by the Mareſchals <hi>de la Mêleraye,</hi> take the Town, Caſtle, and Citadel of <hi>Piambino</hi> in <hi>Tuſcany;</hi> at which time Monſieur the Marquiſs <hi>Villeroy,</hi> the King's Governour, received from the hands of their Majeſties the Oath of Mareſchal of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Portolongona,</hi> a place ſcituated in the Iſle of <hi>Elb,</hi> lying in the <hi>Tuſcan</hi>-Sea between the Continent of <hi>Italy</hi> and <hi>Corſica,</hi> which was heretofore uſurp'd from its own lawful Lord by a Captain of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the 5th, in the year 1548. after that delivered into the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:135098:24"/>
poſſeſſion of his ſon <hi>Philip</hi> the 2d, and whoſe Succeſſors held it ever ſince, was now Beſieged and taken by the French Army. In the midſt of this Iſland ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes a Spring, on this account the more admirable, that its Waters are obſerved to hold proportion with the length of the daies of the year, in ſuch manner, that when they are at the longeſt the Stream is able to drive a Mill, but when at the ſhorteſt 'tis almoſt dry.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Lerida</hi> in <hi>Catalonia</hi> having been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged by the <hi>Comte de Harcour</hi> for the ſpace of 7 moneths, was relieved the 21 of <hi>November,</hi> in the night, by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs <hi>de Leganez</hi> General of the Spaniſh Army; who forcing our Lines with 7000 Foot, and 3000 Horſe, our par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, though at the firſt they made a ſtout reſiſtance, encouraged by the Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of their Commander, yet finding themſelves o'repower'd by the number of the Enemy, were conſtrained to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire (but in good order) into <hi>Cerveres</hi> with 6000 Foot and 1000 Horſe, by that means to ſecure the Country. We
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:135098:25"/>
loſt there the <hi>Comte de Origny:</hi> In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of this action, the Sieur <hi>de</hi> St. <hi>Colom-Marin,</hi> Mareſchal of the Field, took from the Enemy the Town of <hi>Arbera,</hi> the 6th of <hi>December</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>The 26th of the ſame moneth Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam <hi>la Dutcheſs</hi> of <hi>Orleans</hi> was happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered of a ſecond Daughter.</p>
               <p>The ſame day, the 26th of <hi>December,</hi> being the Feaſt of St. <hi>Steven, Henry de Bourbon</hi> Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> deceaſed at <hi>Paris,</hi> aged 58 years and three moneths: he left two Sons and a Daughter, the <note n="*">Formerly called Duke of <hi>Enguien.</hi>
                  </note> Eldeſt of which makes no inconſiderable part in the French Hiſtory of theſe laſt years, by reaſon of his many Renowned Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploits of War, Sieges and Battles, in which things he has rendered his Name Renowned, having joyned <hi>Mars</hi> and <hi>Minerva</hi> in his own perſon. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſon is Monſieur the Prince of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty.</hi> The Daughter <hi>Mademoiſelle de Bourbon,</hi> Married Monſieur the Duke of <hi>Longueville.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1647" type="year">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:135098:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1647.</head>
               <p>In the beginning of the year 1647. though the Winter-ſeaſon invited our Troops rather into Garriſon, yet ſuch was the courage of the Mareſchal <hi>de Gaſſion,</hi> that nothing relenting at the extremity of the Weather, he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes the ſiege of <hi>Ingelmunſter;</hi> the Garriſon of which place was no ſmall impediment in our Victualling <hi>Courtray.</hi> This place was Attaqu'd with ſuch fury, that ſhe was forced to yield by the end of <hi>February.</hi> The Governour with his Garriſon was conducted to <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray,</hi> having received no other compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition than to remain Priſoners of War. Alſo the Marquiſs of <hi>Marolles,</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Thionville</hi> (a place heretofore taken by the now Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently after his Victory at <hi>Rocroy,</hi> in the year 1643.) about the ſame time de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated a party of the Garriſon of <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emburg,</hi> by means of an Ambuſcade, where he killed and took Priſoners a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove 100 men.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:135098:26"/>About the end of the ſaid Moneth of <hi>February,</hi> the Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne</hi> inveſts <hi>Tubinguen</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and after a Siege of ſeventeen or eighteen daies ſubmits the place to the King's obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence. This did contribute much to the Treaty of Neutrality, not long after concluded with the Duke of <hi>Bavaria,</hi> in which was compriſed the Elector of <hi>Cologne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Since the Arch-Duke <hi>Leopold</hi> had quitted the Conduct of the Imperial Forces to be General in the <hi>Low-Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries,</hi> he had raiſed on the ſuddain a compleat Army, with which he Inveſts <hi>Armentieres,</hi> under the Government of the Sieur <hi>du Pleſſis-Bellievre.</hi> This Siege being ſo ſurprizing, made the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage of our party yield to neceſſity, ſo that for want of Ammunition the place was ſurrendered the 31 of <hi>May.</hi> The Garriſon remained all Priſoners of War, except the Governour and Principal Officers.</p>
               <p>At this time the King and Queen Regent were at <hi>Amiens,</hi> to give their
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:135098:26"/>
orders more effectually for ſecuring the Frontiers of <hi>Picardy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Arch-Duke <hi>Leopold</hi> having ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken <hi>Armentieres,</hi> lays ſiege to <hi>Landre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> where the Garriſon not being ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to ſecure their Outworks, the Sieur <hi>Heudicourt</hi> their Governour, after a courageous defence of three Weeks, was forced to ſurrender the 18th of <hi>July.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Mareſchal <hi>de Gaſſion</hi> finding that he was unable to ſuccour <hi>Landre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi> joyned with the Mareſchal <hi>de Rantzau</hi> to revenge that loſs elſewhere: this laſt in three days made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Dixmude;</hi> and the Mareſchal <hi>de Gaſſion</hi> ſo vigorouſly Aſſaulted <hi>la Baſſée,</hi> that he forced the Beſieged to ſurrender at the end of eight daies. After this, the Mareſchal in one day takes the Fort <hi>Nieufdan</hi> neer <hi>Newport,</hi> and <hi>Sluiſe,</hi> with ſeveral other little Forts, all which he Demoliſh'd. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this, the Marquiſs <hi>de Caracene,</hi> ſent to relieve <hi>Newport</hi> in caſe of a Siege, obliges the Mareſchal to an Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:135098:27"/>
in which Rencounter the Enemy loſt 300 men, and we not above fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen.</p>
               <p>The French Army, being now in ſufficient condition to oppoſe their Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the King and Queen Regent leave <hi>Amiens</hi> the 27th of <hi>July,</hi> and take the way of <hi>Abbeville;</hi> paſſing thence to <hi>Dieppe,</hi> they were received by the <hi>Sieur de Montigny,</hi> who met them in the head of 500 Gentlemen. The 9th of <hi>Auguſt</hi> they arrive at <hi>Paris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Mareſchal <hi>de Rantzau</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Mareſchal <hi>de Gaſſion</hi> was neceſſitated to remain in the midſt of his Enemies to keep <hi>la Baſſée,</hi> makes a ſhew of beſieging <hi>Lens;</hi> and by that means having diverted the Enemy, and brought off <hi>Gaſſion</hi> from all danger, attaques the Troops of Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> lately arrived from <hi>Luxemburg,</hi> and defeats 800 men, of which he took 200 Priſoners. Preſently after, the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of theſe two Generals being uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the 10th of <hi>September,</hi> march againſt the Common Enemy, and often
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:135098:27"/>
Skirmiſh, but always with advantage on our ſide.</p>
               <p>The 23 of <hi>September,</hi> our Army having paſt the River <hi>Lis,</hi> the next day arrives before <hi>Lens:</hi> The Mareſchal <hi>Gaſſion</hi> took the plain of <hi>Doway,</hi> and the <hi>Sieur de Villequier</hi> the Bridge <hi>Avandin:</hi> the night following they opened their Trenches, and the 26th the Cannon began to batter; but the Mareſchal <hi>Gaſſion</hi> being on his way to ſuccour the <hi>Sieur de Villequier</hi> at the Bridge <hi>Avan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>din,</hi> and underſtanding that the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had taken it, returns to the Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               <p>The 28th he hearing that the Beſie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged had raiſed a Palliſade neer the Town-gate, he gives order that the Poſts be immediately pluck'd up: and being told it was a matter of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary danger, by reaſon of the Enemies continual firing from that quarter; he goes thither himſelf, and as he was trying to move one of the Poſts, receives a Muſquet-ſhot in the ſide of his head, with which he falls from his Horſe; and being
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:135098:28"/>
taken up and carried to <hi>Arras,</hi> deceaſed the 10th of <hi>October,</hi> in the 38th year of his Age.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Sieur de Villequier</hi> continues the ſiege of <hi>Lens,</hi> and that with ſuch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution and effect, that the Beſieged are forced to ſurrender the third of the ſame <hi>October;</hi> and the <hi>Comte de Palluau, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre de Camp</hi> of the Cavalry, took poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of the place with a French Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon.</p>
               <p>In the mean time the Enemy think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to divert the ſiege of <hi>Lens,</hi> beſiege <hi>Dixmude;</hi> which place, after a coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous reſiſtance on our part, was forced to ſurrender.</p>
               <p>The Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne</hi> receiving orders from the King to march into <hi>Germany,</hi> underſtands that Major-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral <hi>Roſe</hi> by ſecret practiſes had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched ſeveral Souldiers of his Troops; hereupon, having firſt endeavoured by all means poſſible to reclaim him to his duty, though ineffectually; to prevent a greater diſorder, he ſecures his perſon, and ſends him Priſoner to <hi>Philipsburg.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:135098:28"/>About this time, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> under the Conduct of <hi>Bonichauſen,</hi> Mareſchal <hi>de Camp Imperial,</hi> Colonel <hi>Frangipani</hi> Governour of <hi>Frankendal,</hi> and Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel <hi>Garnier,</hi> form a deſigne to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege <hi>Worms,</hi> the Garriſon conſiſting but of 100 men. The Sieur <hi>de la Marche,</hi> Governour of the place, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the weakneſs of the place, and being preſt by the Enemy who had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſtruck a terrour into the Citizens, engaged to ſurrender, in caſe he recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved no relief in two daies. Hereupon he ſends immediately to the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Philipsburg,</hi> who diſpatches the <hi>Sieur de la Poquetiere</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Touraine,</hi> with 100 men, who guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with other Succours, paſs the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, enter the Town, and without ever reſting Sally immediately at another Gate on the oppoſite ſide, charging the Enemy in that quarter ſo courage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, that in fine they beat them off, and<note n="*">That is, to drive a Nail or Iron-pin into the Touch-hole, ſo that they become uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</note> Nail'd their Cannon, in ſuch manner, that the Enemy
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:135098:29"/>
finding no hopes of gaining the place, quitted the ſiege.</p>
               <p>In <hi>Catalonia,</hi> the Mareſchal <hi>de Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mont,</hi> by order of the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> having purſued the <hi>Spaniards</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieged <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> return'd and joyns with our Army the 12 of <hi>October;</hi> and the 21, Monſieur the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving drawn together all our Troops, on advice that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> under the Conduct of the Marquiſs <hi>d'Aietone</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to fight us, and with deſigne to engage them marches towards <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouche,</hi> about three hours journey from <hi>Lesborges,</hi> between <hi>Lerida</hi> and the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy; but perceiving them to retreat towards <hi>Lerida,</hi> he ſends the Marquiſs <hi>de la Trouſſe</hi> to intercept their way, and follows himſelf upon their Rear. The Enemy, who thought of nothing but a ſafe Retreat to <hi>Lerida,</hi> and now ſeeing themſelves encompaſt by the Mareſchal <hi>de Gramont</hi>'s Forces, prepare for fight; and they had undoubtedly beat our party, had not Monſieur the Prince, ſeeing the hazard, advanced and ſtopt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:135098:29"/>
their ſucceſs: but by the favour of the Night, which came on apace, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſt the <hi>Segre,</hi> with the loſs of ſeven or eight hundred men, cut in pieces by our Forces. We loſt there the <hi>Sieur de Lupes St. Remy</hi> a Captain, <hi>de Serre</hi> a Cornet, and ſome Common Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</p>
               <p>The 24th of <hi>October, Tutavilla</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour of <hi>Terragona,</hi> preſenting him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf again before <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> was again beaten off by the Troops of Monſieur the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and the diligence of the <hi>Sieur de la Baume</hi> Governour of the place.</p>
               <p>This year 1647. concludes with the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi>'s entry into <hi>Naples,</hi> the <hi>Neapolitans</hi> (who of a long time had been oppreſt with the Spaniſh Yoak) having invited him, and put themſelves under his protection, during his abode at <hi>Rome.</hi> Embarquing then the third of <hi>November,</hi> attended onely with his <hi>Aumoſnier</hi> and the Gentleman of his Chamber, he arrived happily at <hi>Naples</hi> the fifth, and was there received with
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:135098:30"/>
incredible joy of the Inhabitants, who had made a ſhift to defend themſelves to that preſent againſt the Spaniſh Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, notwithſtanding their many Conſpiracies; and had alſo expel'd all thoſe whom they ſuſpected of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Faction. Here the Machinations of the other party were ſo great and dangerous, that the Duke run many hazards.</p>
               <p>From the year 1280, in which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the Maſſacre of the French in <hi>Sicily,</hi> under <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Anjou</hi> firſt of that Name, and Brother of St. <hi>Lewis,</hi> to the time of <hi>René d'Anjou, Naples</hi> had been the conſtant Field of Battle in all the Conteſts between the Houſes of <hi>Anjou</hi> and <hi>Aragon,</hi> as is obſerved in the courſe of the French Hiſtory, where we may ſee how <hi>Charles</hi> the 2d ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded to his Father in that Kingdom, and after his death his ſon <hi>Robert.</hi> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, about the year 1344, <hi>Joan</hi> the firſt of that Name, Daughter of <hi>Charles</hi> a Son of the ſaid <hi>Robert,</hi> ſucceeded to the Crown of <hi>Naples. Joan</hi> ending
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:135098:30"/>
her life by a ſad and ſhameful death, <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> ſon to <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Durazo</hi> ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, about the year 1387. and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in poſſeſſion of the Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> till his death. <hi>Ladiſlaus</hi> dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Joan</hi> the 2d his Siſter ſucceeds, in the year 1417. who finding her ſelf continually moleſted by thoſe of the Houſe of <hi>Aragon,</hi> declares <hi>René d'Anjou</hi> her Heir and Succeſſor, about the year 1435. But whether it was that his own peaceful Inclinations, or the Inconſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of the <hi>Neapolitan</hi> humour ſtop'd his deſignes, is uncertain: this is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, he never did any thing effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally towards the Conqueſt of that Kingdom, to which his Birth-right did call him. This gave opportunity to <hi>Ferdinand</hi> ſon of <hi>Alphonſo</hi> to ſeize the Scepter, notwithſtanding <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Calabria</hi> ſon of <hi>René</hi> attempted (though in vain) to recover the right of his Grandfathers: But <hi>Charles</hi> the 8th, King of <hi>France,</hi> undertook this Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize with ſuch a courage, that all <hi>Italy</hi> lay open to his Arms; and having firſt
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:135098:31"/>
made his entry into <hi>Rome,</hi> he was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived at <hi>Naples</hi> with extraordinary magnificence, in the year 1494. <hi>Charles</hi> after this retiring into <hi>France,</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> the 12th extending his Conqueſts to <hi>Milain, Francis</hi> the firſt deſiring to extend them ſtill further, at ſuch time as he Beſieged <hi>Pavie,</hi> divided his Army, and ſent half for <hi>Naples;</hi> but his being taken Priſoner on the 24th of <hi>February,</hi> in the year 1525, put a period to thoſe deſignes. From that time to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, <hi>Naples</hi> ever remained under the Dominion of the <hi>Spaniards.</hi> And this laſt Change being ſo notorious, we have made this ſhort recapitulation of the ſeveral viciſſitudes of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>From the time of <hi>Francis</hi> the firſt, to <hi>Lewis</hi> 13th, and <hi>Lewis</hi> 14th, ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily raigning at preſent, the power of <hi>Spain</hi> was arrived to that point, that in fine it ſeemed all <hi>Europe</hi> ſhould ſpeak no other Language than <hi>Spaniſh:</hi> but God, whoſe Dominion extends over all Monarchies, hath in a few years dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:135098:31"/>
the ſwelling extent of this, which now of late begins, by little and little, to fall within its ancient limits.</p>
               <p>But to return to the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> after this little digreſſion, and obſerve ſome of the principal actions which at that time he performed in thoſe parts; we muſt know then in ſhort: This Prince, on his arrival perceiving how much the people were oppreſs'd by the Spaniſh Dominion, in the firſt place diſpatches ſeveral Couriers to all thoſe Towns which he conceived moſt material to contribute to the overthrow of their Authority; and after he had duly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of all things, by his rare Conduct, he viſits the ſaid places ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and takes an exact view of all their Ammunitions: after this, he raiſes 26000 men, which he diſtributes into three Bodies. And at the ſame time, <hi>Salerne</hi> falls off to the Republick.</p>
               <p>Hereupon <hi>Dom John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Turſi,</hi> arrive in <hi>Naples</hi> with a Counter Force, to ſtop the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples Mutinies; but they having joyn'd
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:135098:32"/>
Policy and Addreſs to the Arms they had levied, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> could not poſſibly prevent their Choice of our Prince for Duke of the Republick, and Generaliſſimo of all their Forces. But ſince events of War are ſo uncertain, and what ſeems moſt aſſured often wants ſucceſs; Fortune was ſo indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> that our Duke was taken Priſoner by <hi>Tutavilla</hi> at the Paſs of a little River; and this was the utter ruine of the <hi>Neapolitans</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1648" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1648.</head>
               <p>Let us now return to <hi>France.</hi> The King, and Queen Regent his Mother, having been at <hi>Chartres</hi> to pay their Vows to our Lady, return to <hi>Paris</hi> the 27th of <hi>March</hi> 1648.</p>
               <p>In <hi>April,</hi> the Generals of our Armies prepare for a new Campagne, expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting the uſual Progreſs, in adding to their former Conqueſts. According<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, on the 20th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> his Majeſty
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:135098:32"/>
obtained a ſignal Victory before <hi>Lens;</hi> where the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in chief, took Priſoner the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Bek,</hi> who died ſoon after of his Wounds. This had filled all <hi>France</hi> with joy, had not an unexpected acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent diſturbed the Feaſt. On the 26th <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung in the Cathedral of <hi>Noſtre Dame</hi> at <hi>Paris;</hi> and on the ſame day, the Sieurs <hi>de Brouſſel,</hi> and <hi>de Blanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſnil</hi> were Arreſted; which cauſed a great diſorder through all the City, till by the Queens bounty in reſtoring their Liberty, it was appeaſed.</p>
               <p>In the moneth of <hi>January,</hi> the ſame year, the Rebels of <hi>England</hi> had the horrid Impudence to Condemn their King to the Scaffold: After that, forbid the having any other King for the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and changed the Government to a Republick. <hi>Fairfax</hi> was declared General of their Forces, and <hi>Cromwel</hi> his Lieutenant; who ſoon after, on the acquittal of the former, took to himſelf the whole Authority: He made himſelf Maſter of <hi>Scotland, Ireland,</hi> and
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:135098:33"/>
                  <hi>England,</hi> he made and unmade the Parliament at his pleaſure; and in fine, under the name of Protector of the Commonwealth of <hi>England,</hi> he moſt Sacrilegiouſly uſurp'd the Command of a King.</p>
               <p>This year ended with the Peace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>France,</hi> the Emperour, and <hi>Swede,</hi> concluded at <hi>Oſnabruc.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1649" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1649.</head>
               <p>In the year 1649, the King, Queen, and Princes leave <hi>Paris,</hi> in the night between the fifth and ſixth of <hi>January,</hi> and retire to St. <hi>Germains.</hi> The <hi>Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians</hi> believing they intend to revenge their inſolencies committed in the action aforeſaid, take Arms, and riſe in Troops by order of the Prince of <hi>Conty.</hi> Hereupon the King ſeizes St. <hi>Denis, Meudon, Corbeil,</hi> and <hi>Lagny.</hi> This had no doubt occaſioned a publick Ruine, had not the Court of Parliament depu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſeveral of their Members to his Majeſtie, and obtained a general Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtie,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:135098:33"/>
which once more reſtored <hi>France</hi> to her former quiet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1650" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1650.</head>
               <p>In <hi>January</hi> 1650, the Princes of <hi>Condé, Conty,</hi> and Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> were Impriſoned in the <hi>Château de Vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cennes;</hi> from thence removed firſt to <hi>Marcouſſy,</hi> and then to <hi>Havre de Grace,</hi> and reſtored to Liberty the 6th of <hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bruary</hi> 1651. The Princeſs of <hi>Condé</hi> retired to <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> with the Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> her Son, where were alſo the Dukes of <hi>Boüillon, Roche-Foucaut,</hi> and <hi>de Turenne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In this year the Enemy recovered <hi>Piombino,</hi> and <hi>Portolongone, le Catelet, la Capelle,</hi> and <hi>Vervins,</hi> as alſo <hi>Mouſon,</hi> and <hi>Rethel,</hi> which notwithſtanding they kept not long.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1651" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1651.</head>
               <p>Nor was the year 1651 more fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate to us, ſeeing we loſt then <hi>Furnes,</hi> and <hi>Bergue</hi> in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:135098:34"/>And now the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> retires into his Government of <hi>Guienne,</hi> neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lecting to be preſent at the King's Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jority, which was magnificently cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brated the 7th of <hi>September.</hi> Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly after, his Majeſty takes a Journey to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Bourges,</hi> to ſtop the ill intentions of the Princes; which place, upon his approach, they quitted with their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p>The King ſtops not in his deſignes, but marches on towards <hi>Poitou,</hi> takes <hi>St. Amand,</hi> ſends the <hi>Comte de Harcour</hi> to attaque <hi>Rochelle,</hi> which the <hi>Comte d'Ognon</hi> held at the Prince's devotion, and compels him to ſubmit to obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1652" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1652.</head>
               <p>In the mean time the Parliament at <hi>Paris</hi> declares the Cardinal <hi>Mazarin</hi> guilty of High Treaſon; who retires for a while: but not at all to remit ought of his care or occaſion to ſerve his Majeſty, he raiſes ſeveral Troops,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:135098:34"/>
and preſents them to the King at <hi>Poitiers</hi> the 25th of <hi>January</hi> 1652, without having encountered any obſtacle. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this, <hi>Angers</hi> is Beſieged by the Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> and compel'd to ſubmit to the King's obedience, together with <hi>le Pont de Cé.</hi> And now the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to juſtifie his Miniſter, ſends a Declaration to the Parliament at <hi>Paris,</hi> commanding that all the proceedings a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Cardinal <hi>Mazarin</hi> be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with brought over to him.</p>
               <p>The King Beſieges <hi>Eſtampes,</hi> in which place the Army of the Princes was ſhut up; but the Iſſue being not very ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous to the Royal Army, he was forced to draw off, and inveſt <hi>Paris.</hi> Here happened many Attaques on both ſides after the arrival of the <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rainers;</hi> though theſe laſt ſhun'd the Encounter as much as poſſible, in ſuch fort, that they came not hand to hand till ſuch time as they met in the <hi>Faux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg St. Anthoine;</hi> at which Encounter it is believed there died more than 1000 men on both ſides. The Fight endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:135098:35"/>
from ſeven in the Morning till three in the Afternoon. The Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> did all that could be expected from a valiant Captain; nevertheleſs, had not <hi>Mademoiſelle</hi> cauſed the City-Gate to be opened, and the Cannon to be diſcharged from the <hi>Baſtille,</hi> the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the Princes had been utterly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated.</p>
               <p>Two days after this, the diſorder was ſo great in <hi>Paris,</hi> that all people were forced to wear Straw about 'em, as a mark of averſion to the Cardinal <hi>Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin:</hi> After this, they ſet fire to the outward Gates of the <hi>Hoſtel de Ville,</hi> where 300 of the moſt noted Citizens being Aſſembled, to conſult of ſome means whereby to unite the City with the Parliament, the Mutineers, in order to deſtroy them all, firſt Maſſacre the Sieurs <hi>le Gras</hi> Maſter of Requeſts, <hi>de Janvry</hi> Counſellor in the Parliament, <hi>Myron</hi> Maſter of the Accounts, and ſeveral others, as they came out from the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly. The <hi>Sieur Doujat</hi> Counſellor of the Great Chamber, and ſeveral
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:135098:35"/>
other perſons of Condition, had run the ſame fortune, had they not uſed Diſguizes, and by the favour of the night paſt unknown during this diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance. Two of the Factious were Condemned by the Sentence of the Parliament to be Hanged, and were accordingly Executed in the Court of the Palace. The Sedition grew to that extremity, that even the Prieſts, and Religious, Women and Children, were forced to wear Straw, and thereby ſecure themſelves from outrages: nay, the very <hi>Nuns,</hi> who to ſhun the dangers of the Campagne ſought refuge in this City, if at any time they were ſeen in the Streets, or Churches, found themſelves obliged to appear with this ridiculous Badge. The Duke of <hi>Nemours</hi> about this time challenged the Duke of <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort;</hi> they met with Sword and Piſtol: The Duke of <hi>Nemours</hi> fires, but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out further execution than onely to ſinge the Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi>'s Periwig; but he in return fail'd not to kill his Enemy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:135098:36"/>And now the people of <hi>Paris</hi> being pretty well tired with the effects of War, begin to diſguſt the rule of the Princes, and upon this occaſion depute ſeveral of their Burgeſſes to <hi>Pontoiſe,</hi> where the King then was, to ſupplicate his Majeſty to honour his good Town of <hi>Paris</hi> with his return. This occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned the retreat of the Duke of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans,</hi> and flight of the Prince of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dé</hi> with his Troops. Not long after, the King returns to the City, followed by the Mareſchal <hi>de l'Hoſpital</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the place, the <hi>Prevoſt des Merchands,</hi> and the <hi>Eſchevins,</hi> who had been all conſtrained to abſent; and was there received with all the ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and bleſſings which the people could poſſibly invent.</p>
               <p>After this, the King went to the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, which he re-unites with that part which he had lately eſtabliſh'd at <hi>Pontoiſe.</hi> And then and there alſo he publiſhes his Amneſtie, in favour of all thoſe who had riſen, provided that by their returning to duty they made
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:135098:36"/>
themſelves capable of ſuch a Grace. But the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> being retired into the Catholick King's Dominions, appeared in the head of an Army be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Rhetel,</hi> of which ſoon after he got poſſeſſion, as alſo of <hi>Chaſteau-Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cien, Sainte-Menchou,</hi> and <hi>Bar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>During the troubles at <hi>Paris,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> knowing the Mareſchal <hi>de Grancey</hi> to be abſent from <hi>Gravelines,</hi> lay ſiege to that place, and take it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it could poſſibly be ſuccoured on our part.</p>
               <p>Thoſe of <hi>Guienne</hi> finding themſelves in ſuch diſorder by reaſon of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces party, invite the King's Army to come among them, commanded by the Count <hi>de Harcour,</hi> who retakes <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beſieux, Pondeſat,</hi> and <hi>la Reole;</hi> though the Baron of <hi>Vatteville</hi> was come into the River of <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> to aſſiſt the Princes, on the part of the Catholick King; who ſerving himſelf of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent troubles, ſent <hi>Dom John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria</hi> to Beſiege <hi>Barcelona,</hi> of which with much eaſe he became Maſter. However,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:135098:37"/>
the loſs was in ſome ſort repaired by the reduction of <hi>Mont-rond;</hi> of which place, the Mareſchal <hi>de Palluau,</hi> who Commanded at the Siege, had order to caſt down the Fortifications.</p>
               <p>Towards the end of this Campagne, the meaſure of our diſgraces was arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to that fulneſs, as to looſe alſo <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> and <hi>Caſal;</hi> the firſt to the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> the other to the Duke of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Cardinal <hi>de Rets,</hi> Coadjutor of <hi>Paris,</hi> having been arreſted in the <hi>Louvre</hi> by the Sieur <hi>de Villequier,</hi> was conducted to the <hi>Bois de Vincennes,</hi> where having been detained for a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable time, was from thence con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed by the Mareſchal <hi>de la Mêleraye</hi> to the Caſtle of <hi>Nantes,</hi> from which in the open day he eſcaped, firſt to <hi>Belle</hi>-Iſle, and then to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Marquiſs of <hi>Vieville,</hi> Super-In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant of the Finances, being deceaſed, the Sieur <hi>de Servient,</hi> and the Sieur <hi>Fouquet</hi> Attorney-General, were joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly put into the Office.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:135098:37"/>Alſo the Cardinal <hi>Antonio Barberin</hi> had the Office of Grand Aumoſnier of <hi>France,</hi> confer'd the 8th of <hi>April,</hi> late void by the death of the Cardinal of <hi>Lyons.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1653" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1653.</head>
               <p>The year 1653. began ſucceſsfully in <hi>Bourgogne; Bellegarde</hi> is beſieged by the Duke of <hi>Eſpernon</hi> Governour of that Province, and in ſpite of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs of <hi>Bouteville</hi>'s reſiſtance who Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the place for the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> he forced a ſubmiſſion to the Arms of his Majeſty. <hi>Rhetel, Mouzon,</hi> and St. <hi>Menehou,</hi> not long after follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſame fortune. But the taking of <hi>Rocroy</hi> by the Prince, abated a little the publick joy for theſe advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges.</p>
               <p>This Succeſs was followed by the reduction of <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> and all the other Towns of <hi>Guyenne</hi> who had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Arms in the Rebellion. As alſo by the accommodement of the Prince
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:135098:38"/>
of <hi>Conty,</hi> and the Dutcheſs of <hi>Longue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ville,</hi> who came in to the Amneſtie; but the Princeſs of <hi>Condé</hi> refuſing to uſe that favour, put her ſelf directly on the way to <hi>Flanders</hi> with her ſon the Duke of <hi>Enguien.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1654" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1654.</head>
               <p>On the 19th of <hi>January</hi> 1654, the King being ſeated in his Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, at which were preſent a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient number of Peers, Proceſs was commenced againſt <hi>Lewis de Bourbon,</hi> Prince of <hi>Condé;</hi> which ended the 27th of <hi>March.</hi> About the end of <hi>May,</hi> his Majeſty took his Journey towards <hi>Rheims,</hi> to be there Crowned and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed: he arrived the third of <hi>June;</hi> and being received by the Burgeſſes and Inhabitants with extraordinary teſtimonials of love, he was conducted to the Cathedral of <hi>Noſtre-Dame,</hi> where the Biſhop of <hi>Soiſſons</hi> attended him, with the Quire and Canons of the Church. The 7th following, was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:135098:38"/>
that admirable Ceremony of his Anointing and Coronation by the ſaid Biſhop, who in that Office repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Rheims.</hi> At the ſame time, the Town of <hi>Stenay</hi> was Beſieged, and forced to ſurrender to the King's obedience; though the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> did his utmoſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it: But the Prince acknowledging the loſs unavoidable, immediately march'd the whole Force of the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Army towards <hi>Arras,</hi> to which he lays ſiege with 30000 men, and all this before our Generals could poſſibly put into the place any Succours conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able: Here he made a Circumvallation that ſeemed to defie all the force of the World: notwithſtanding, the Lines that compaſſed it, how dreadful ſoever, were ſo vigorouſly attaqued by our Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, ſent to endeavour the relief, that the Enemies were conſtrained to abandon their deſignes, ſufficient to intimidate any Nation but the French. We gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by this flight of theirs (which happened on <hi>St. Lewis</hi>'s day) ſixty
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:135098:39"/>
pieces of Cannon, and all the Bag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage of the Beſiegers: 'Tis alſo poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble they had all found their Graves on the place, had not the Prince (the Arch-Duke and other Chiefs having left him) beſtir'd himſelf more than ordinary to aſſwage the precipitate vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olence of the retreat.</p>
               <p>The Mareſchal <hi>de la Ferte-Seneterre,</hi> deſirous to end the Campagne as glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly as it was begun and continued this year, led the Body which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded before <hi>Clermont,</hi> which he Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieges and takes. In the mean time our other Chiefs obſerve the broken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the Spaniſh Army, which all the Winter did nothing but onely threa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Queſnoy;</hi> which place was ſo well furniſh'd by the Marquiſs <hi>de Chaſtelnau,</hi> aſſiſted by the Marquiſs <hi>de Monpoüil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon,</hi> and the <hi>Chevalier de Maupeou,</hi> that ſhe found her ſelf in no condition to fear her Enemies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1655" type="year">
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:135098:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1655.</head>
               <p>The beginning of the year 1655, was remarkable for the deceaſe of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> 10th, happening on the 7th of <hi>January:</hi> after whoſe death the Cardinals entering the Conclave the 17th of the ſame moneth, and there continuing till the 7th of <hi>April,</hi> where all the Embaſſadors were alſo preſent to perform their Complements; they elected to the Holy Seat Cardinal <hi>Chiſi,</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Sienna,</hi> as the moſt worthy in the Sacred Colledge: he had been in all the conſiderable Offices belonging to the Chair of <hi>Rome,</hi> and being now in the ſupreameſt, took the name of <hi>Alexander</hi> 7th. His inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to Peace gave hopes that he would procure it to <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> provided he found the <hi>Spaniard</hi> as much diſpoſed to it as <hi>France;</hi> which hopes we have at length ſeen happily effected.</p>
               <p>About this time the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> arrived from <hi>Naples.</hi> And the Court
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:135098:40"/>
thought convenient to ſend into <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> to purchaſe there a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Ships for the King's ſervice.</p>
               <p>In <hi>May</hi> 1655, Monſieur the Prince of <hi>Conty,</hi> Lieutenant-Generaliſſimo, and Vice-roy for his Majeſty in <hi>Catalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> took by Aſſault <hi>Cap-de Tiers;</hi> and in <hi>July,</hi> continuing the courſe of his Victories, he took <hi>Chaſtillon</hi> and <hi>Saul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſone.</hi> No leſs glorious ſucceſs had our Arms in <hi>Flanders</hi> than in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> by the taking of <hi>Landrecy,</hi> in the face of 35000 men, which being all their force, our Enemies had united, if poſſible, to ſecure this important place, but the event rendered their endeavours to no purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Following the courſe of our ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful projects, in <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the ſame year, we took <hi>Condé,</hi> and <hi>St. Guillain;</hi> the King commanding there in perſon, and having for his Lieutenant-Generals <hi>de Turenne,</hi> and <hi>la Ferté-Seneterre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>November</hi> following, Peace was concluded and proclaimed between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England;</hi> the Treaty was
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:135098:40"/>
made at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> Monſieur <hi>de Bour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deaux</hi> being Embaſſador from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to the ſaid Republick.</p>
               <p>During this year, the Dukes of <hi>Mantua</hi> and <hi>Modena</hi> arrived in <hi>France,</hi> to perform to his Majeſty their ſeveral Homages. Then arrived alſo his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my Cardinal <hi>Antonio Barberin</hi> Nephew to the late Pope <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the 8th, named by his Majeſty for his Grand <hi>Aumoſnier</hi> in place of the decaſed Cardinal of <hi>Lyons.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1656" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1656.</head>
               <p>On the third of <hi>January,</hi> being the Feaſt of <hi>St. Geneviefve,</hi> 1656, <hi>Meſſire Matthew Molé, Gardes Sceaux</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> deceaſed about ſeven in the Morning, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter three daies ſickneſs, in the 72 year of his age; during which time he had paſt moſt of the chief Offices belonging to his robe; namely, that of the Preſident of Requeſts of the Palace; Attorney-General in the Parliament, which place he exerciſed neer 27 years; firſt Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:135098:41"/>
in the ſaid Aſſembly neer thirteen years, and laſtly <hi>Gard de Sceaux;</hi> and all theſe with a marvelous integrity and fidelity to the King's ſervice. The next day the Chancelier of <hi>France</hi> coming to attend the King according to the orders ſent him by the Sieur <hi>Mancini,</hi> his Majeſty by the advice of his Eminency, gave him the Seals in the Queens preſence, with all poſſible demonſtrations of the juſt eſteem which he had for this ſo eminent and ſage Head of the French Juſtice.</p>
               <p>In the ſame year, the King having laid ſiege to <hi>Valenciennes,</hi> where the Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne</hi> commanded in the quality of Lieutenant-General; and having now reduced this impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant place, and the Spaniſh Forces to their very laſt effort; but not being able to prevent the ſuccours, he raiſed the ſiege. Though immediately after, his Majeſtie's Army in <hi>Italy,</hi> under the conduct of the Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> took <hi>Valence;</hi> and at the ſame time his ſaid Majeſty forced <hi>la Capelle</hi> to ſubmiſſion,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:135098:41"/>
in ſight of the Enemy's Army, conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting of more than 30000 men.</p>
               <p>On the 8th of <hi>September,</hi> the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Chriſtina,</hi> late Queen of <hi>Swede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> after ſhe had abjured Hereſie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Pope's own hands at <hi>Rome,</hi> and reſigned her Kingdom to her Cozin <hi>Charles Guſtavus,</hi> Prince Palatine, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived at <hi>Paris,</hi> where ſhe was moſt mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificently received; after this, and that ſhe had ſaluted the King at <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piegne,</hi> ſhe returned to <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This year ended happily with a Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Jubile, which began the firſt <hi>Sunday</hi> of <hi>Advent,</hi> and ended the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>January</hi> 1657.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1657" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1657.</head>
               <p>This year begins with the loſs of the Town of <hi>St. Guillain,</hi> which the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards recovered from us, the Garriſon retiring to <hi>Guiſe</hi> after an honourable Capitulation.</p>
               <p>The ſeaſon now approaching to draw into the Campagne, Monſieur
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:135098:42"/>
the Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne</hi> took the way of <hi>Flanders,</hi> there to command our Forces: The King followed not long after, making his Family immediately ſet forwards for <hi>Compeigne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>le Mareſchal de la Ferté</hi> having alſo directed his march towards <hi>Luxemburg</hi> with a conſiderable Army, Monſieur the Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne</hi> aſſiſting him at a diſtance with his Troops, he inveſts <hi>Montmedy</hi> the 11th of <hi>June,</hi> and wrought at the Lines with ſuch a reſolution, that in ſpight of all reſiſtance from the Beſieged, they were compleated the 15th following. In regard this place was of ſuch impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance to the Catholick King, the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh Commanders did their utmoſt to relieve it; but with no ſucceſs, and therefore they think of ſome other way. Having then intelligence that the Garriſon of <hi>Calais</hi> had been of late much weakened by the abſence of 300 men, drawn off from thence to re-inforce that at <hi>Ardres,</hi> they reſolve to attaque it at unawares; but it reſiſted
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:135098:42"/>
with ſo much glory, that the Aſſailants, not able to effect their deſignes, retired with ſhame.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> unable to relieve <hi>Montmedy,</hi> the Inhabitants were forced to capitulate, the 6th of <hi>Auguſt.</hi> The Garriſon, conſiſting of 300 Muſqueteers and 100 Horſe, left the place, and were conducted within ſight of the Walls of <hi>Arlon.</hi> The King entred, and viewed the Walls round, on Horſeback. He made the Baron <hi>de St. Pé</hi> Governour, to whoſe place not long after ſucceeded the Marquiſs <hi>de Vandy,</hi> one of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie's Generals, and Camp-Maſter to the Carabines.</p>
               <p>The Conqueſt of <hi>Montmedy,</hi> was followed by that of <hi>St. Venant;</hi> from which place the Spaniards deſiring to divert our Arms, made a ſhew to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taque <hi>Ardres;</hi> where notwithſtanding they were forced ſhamefully to raiſe their ſiege, with the loſs of the entire Regiment of <hi>Perſan,</hi> who were all cut to pieces. The reſt of this Campagne paſt in petty Skirmiſhes; in particular,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:135098:43"/>
the Garriſon of <hi>Rocroy</hi> was ſoundly beaten in ſeeking to raiſe a Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion among the neighbour Villages.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dom John</hi> of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> and ſeveral Troops with them, having put themſelves into <hi>Dunkirk</hi> on ſome deſigne, the Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne</hi> on his part prepares to attaque <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dike;</hi> which he did ſo effectually, that it was ſoon after ſurrendered to the diſcretion of our Commanders, the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy having deferred to capitulate, till it was too late.</p>
               <p>We were no leſs happy in <hi>Italy.</hi> The Caſtle of <hi>Monteri</hi> ſurrendered to the force of our Arms; ſo alſo did the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Non,</hi> which was taken before the very face of the <hi>Comte de Fuenſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daigne,</hi> by the Prince of <hi>Conty.</hi> After this, we inveſt <hi>Alexandria;</hi> but the ſiege there was no ſooner formed, but raiſed again, and that for the Conqueſt of <hi>Montecalvo,</hi> and the Caſtle of <hi>Monts,</hi> places which made us Maſters of <hi>Monferrat.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nothing conſiderable paſt this year
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:135098:43"/>
in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> where at that time the Duke of <hi>Candale</hi> commanded, but died in his return at <hi>Lyons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Magazine of Powder in the Town-houſe at <hi>Bourdeaux</hi> took fire, by ſome accident, which reduced that poor Town into a deplorable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. This misfortune happened on the third of <hi>December.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the 10th deceaſing, (as aforeſaid) <hi>Alexander</hi> the 7th ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Papacy, who deſiring above all things to ſee the two greateſt Kings of <hi>Europe</hi> united in a Peace, propoſed it firſt to his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, and endeavoured to incline him: but he received for anſwer, that the onely ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction lay on the part of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, and that he was always moſt wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1658" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1658.</head>
               <p>This ſo generous Declaration thus happily opening the way, gave no ſmall hopes for the effecting ſo great a good:
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:135098:44"/>
but firſt his Majeſty found himſelf ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to force the <hi>Spaniards</hi> to reaſon, by a further purſuit of his Victories, beginning with the ſiege of <hi>Dunkirk;</hi> which ſoon after being taken, he put it into the hands of <hi>Milord Lockhart</hi> the Engliſh Embaſſador, conditionally that he ſhould permit no violence to the Religion of the Inhabitants.</p>
               <p>The taking of this place, though of chief concern, 'twas too ſmall a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt for our Invincible Monarch. The Battle of <hi>Dunes,</hi> which we gained in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely, with the addition of <hi>Bergues, St. Winox, Furnes,</hi> and <hi>Dixmude,</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed this gallant Enterprize. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> were ſeized with terrour at the ſight of ſo many Conqueſts; and the conſternation was ſo great among them, that at the very name of the <hi>French</hi> they took their heels before <hi>Newport,</hi> with the loſs of 800 Horſe and 3000 Cows, which our party took without any reſiſtance.</p>
               <p>Amidſt ſo many Lawrels, our invin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cible Monarch was aſſaulted by a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:135098:44"/>
Feaver, which in a little time re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced him to much extremity; but God, who is always vigilant for the conſervation of Kingdoms, reſtored this young <hi>Mars</hi> to his people, beyond all their hopes. His health being thus recovered, his Majeſty leaves <hi>Calais,</hi> to return to <hi>Paris,</hi> where all the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Courts, and the Burgeſſes, went out to meet him, teſtifying with how great joy they had received the happy news of his recovery, of which they had been almoſt deſperate.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, the Mareſchals <hi>de Turenne,</hi> and <hi>la Ferté,</hi> to whoſe care his Majeſty had left his Army, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the glorious progreſs of their ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful undertakings; Having then firſt taken <hi>Moncaſſel,</hi> they inveſt <hi>Gravelines</hi> under the conduct of Monſieur the Mareſchal <hi>de Bellefons;</hi> which place, after a ſtout defence by the Beſieged, who fought in deſpair, was reduced to a Capitulation, as when taken from us, at ſuch time as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> made uſe of our Civil Wars. The <hi>Chevalier de
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:135098:45"/>
Hautefeville</hi> Captain of the Regiment of Guards, entred the 31 day of the ſiege with three Companies of the ſaid Regiment; and the <hi>Sieur Davignan</hi> was, the next day, left Governour till fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther order.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Spaniards</hi> foreſeeing they were about to loſe all that they had in theſe parts, did their utmoſt endeavours to ſecure what they could poſſibly: but the diſcreet vigilancy of Monſieur the Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne</hi> did always fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate their deſignes. They were not able to ſuccour <hi>Oudenarde,</hi> which ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendered immediately to the <hi>French</hi> valour: they were glad to take covert in <hi>Armentiers,</hi> and <hi>Tournay,</hi> for fear of being engaged to Battle; where with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt they would have been bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, ſince in all our Encounters, For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune had ſeemed to forſake them, and to confer her Victories on us.</p>
               <p>The King deſigning to viſit <hi>Lyons,</hi> arrives at <hi>Dijon,</hi> where receiving ſome diſcontents from his Parliament, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terdicts them immediately, and purſues
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:135098:45"/>
his Journey to <hi>Lyons,</hi> at which place he was received with incredible joy from all people: And here it was that he received the complements of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame Royale,</hi> who came to viſit him with the Princeſſes her Daughters. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo his Royal Highneſs of <hi>Savoy</hi> preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted himſelf with a very conſiderable Retinue, extraordinary well furniſh'd. Two days after, his ſaid Highneſs par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted again for <hi>Turin,</hi> but with a moſt entire ſatisfaction at the ſight of our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Prince. The Deputies of the Eſtates of <hi>Languedoc,</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Provence,</hi> had Audience; but the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of <hi>Savoy</hi> had a particular one, as alſo the Envoy of the Duke of <hi>Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tua.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Since, in the beginning of the year, all things did ſeem to concur to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Lawrels of our young <hi>Mars</hi> more reſplendant, all people began now to talk of Peace. To that purpoſe, a Ceſſation from acts of Hoſtility was publiſh'd on both ſides, to the end they might have the more liberty to treat
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:135098:46"/>
of the future tranquillity: and this daughter of Heaven, which God alone gives to his people, after he has Chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed 'em, was equally deſired by both parties. Monſieur <hi>de Lyonne,</hi> then, is ſent into <hi>Spain,</hi> and the Sieur <hi>Pimentel</hi> arrived at <hi>Lyons,</hi> during the King's a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bode there: this appeared a good and hopeful beginning, ſince both Nations began of themſelves to re-aſſume their former Traffique, ſo long diſcontinued.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1659" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1659.</head>
               <p>Hereupon the Cardinal <hi>Mazarin,</hi> accompanied by the Duke of <hi>Crequy,</hi> the Mareſchals <hi>de Villeroy, de Clerem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baud,</hi> the Grand Maſter of the Artil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, the Sieur <hi>de Lyonne,</hi> and a great number of other Lords, takes the way of the Frontier, where <hi>Dom Lewis d'Haro</hi> chief Miniſter of <hi>Spain</hi> would meet him of <hi>France,</hi> to confer to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for the perfecting ſo great a Work.</p>
               <p>The Truce was already prolong'd to
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:135098:46"/>
further order; but before they begin the Conference, it was agreed that Monſieur <hi>de Lyonne</hi> ſhould have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to meet and complement the Miniſter of <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Dom Antonio Pimentel</hi> to perform the like civilities to him of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Monſieur <hi>de Lyonne</hi> had order to propoſe to the <hi>Spaniards</hi> a Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween their <hi>Infanta</hi> and the King of <hi>France:</hi> and in regard their chief fear was, that in default of Male-Children to ſucceed to that Crown, that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom might fall to the King of <hi>France,</hi> their Queens being now with Childe cauſed that apprehenſion to vaniſh, and rendered them the more attentive to this Alliance. Notwithſtanding procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings were for a time broken, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of a difficulty preſented on the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half of the Prince of <hi>Condé,</hi> whom the King of <hi>Spain</hi> would have compriſed in the Treaty. Cardinal <hi>Mazarin</hi> therefore writ to the Pope, to perſwade that King to wave the Prince's Intereſt, and not for that to defer ſo precious
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:135098:47"/>
a benefit to both Nations. The <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> during this year, were in as bad a condition with the <hi>Portugals,</hi> and that made them the more eaſily incline to wave this Article. The Alliance which about this time <hi>France</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted with <hi>England,</hi> and the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of Madam <hi>Royale</hi> and his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, had given them ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient cauſe of jealouſie: They went, therefore, ſeriouſly to work to effect the Treaty; and during the Winter, the King being returned to <hi>Paris, Pimentel</hi> follows him thither, and renews the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions of Peace and Marriage; to which Cardinal <hi>Mazarin</hi> and D. <hi>Lewis d'Haro</hi> conferred the finiſhing hand. Theſe two great Miniſters being arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the Iſle of <hi>Pheſants,</hi> upon the River <hi>Bidaſſoa,</hi> with a moſt magnificent Train, after many notable Interviews and Conferences from the one part and the other, at laſt ſigne the Treaty of Peace, and Contract of Marriage be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Spain</hi> and the King of <hi>France.</hi> Notwithſtanding the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:135098:47"/>
Publication was not made immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that being reſerved to render the enſuing year more Auguſt and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous: the preſent, concluding with all diſpoſitions requiſite to our future hopes of an eternal happineſs, and a laſting Tranquillity to both Kingdoms, which not a year ago none dared to promiſe or expect.</p>
               <p>The Peace then being proclaimed, his Holineſs, and all the Potentates and Soveraigns of <hi>Europe,</hi> expreſs'd their publick joys and ſatisfaction, in thoſe many <hi>feux de joye</hi> which they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded their people to make through all their Dominions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1660" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1660.</head>
               <p>The Peace was Regiſter'd in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment the 12th of <hi>February,</hi> the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celier being preſent, and with univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal applauſe and acclamations.</p>
               <p>In <hi>England,</hi> General <hi>Monke</hi> was ſo happy this year, as to contribute very much to the Reſtauration of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:135098:48"/>
                  <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, the lawful and undoubted Heir and Succeſſor to that Crown.</p>
               <p>To put a compleat end to a War, which had laſted 25 Campagnes, the King reſolves on a Progreſs, thereby al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to compoſe for ever the Factions in <hi>Provence,</hi> and reduce to reaſon certain Pirates of <hi>Marſeilles,</hi> who becoming petty-Tyrants, did much oppreſs that important City. The Duke of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coeur</hi> entred the place, Sword in Hand, at the head of the King's Light-horſe. The prudence and moderation of this Prince ſecured the Town from Pillage; and he obſerved ſo much order and cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſpection in this affair, that he ſoon reduced the place to great obedience. After this, the King himſelf was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved there with Volleys of Cannon, and the joyful cries of <hi>Vive le Roy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>During this Journey, he cauſed to be demoliſhed the Citadel of <hi>Orenge,</hi> which heretofore had been the cauſe of much miſchief to the Catholicks of the three neighbouring Provinces, and
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:135098:48"/>
was ſtill ſuſpected; and withal, charged the Prince of <hi>Orenge,</hi> that hereafter he keep a more ſtrong and able Garriſon.</p>
               <p>To ſecure the <hi>Marſellois</hi> from all fears of their paſt miſeries, the King cauſed to be traced out the Platform of a Citadel, and this for the future to contain the Nobleſs and Citizens in their duty. His Majeſty being at <hi>Aix,</hi> with much joy and tenderneſs recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> at his return from the <hi>Low-Countries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Majeſties continuing their Progreſs through <hi>Languedoc,</hi> were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived moſt magnificently at <hi>Thoulouſe,</hi> and then at <hi>Bourdeaux,</hi> paſſing from thence to <hi>Bayonne,</hi> and ſo to <hi>St. John Luz,</hi> they arrived in the Iſle of <hi>Phea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants,</hi> where was appointed the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>view of the two Kings, and the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious reception of <hi>Maria-Thereſa d'Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> Inheretrix preſumptive to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of his Catholick Majeſty. The Pomp and Conſummation of theſe ſo great and ſplendid Nuptials, was very advantageous to the two Crowns. The
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:135098:49"/>
Ceremonies performed, their Majeſties take the Road of <hi>Paris,</hi> and arrive happily at the <hi>Bois de Vincennes,</hi> where for ſome daies they reſt, till the Queens moſt magnifique entry at <hi>Paris,</hi> the 26th of <hi>Auguſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now happens that horrid Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake, at the <hi>Pyrenean</hi>-Hills, which ſwallowing the hot Bathes there, and ſeveral other places, cauſed extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary terrour to the Inhabitants of all that <hi>Voiſinage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The deceaſe of the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> at <hi>Blois,</hi> the 2d of <hi>February,</hi> did much abate our publick Joy and Triumphs, their Majeſties and all the Court being ſenſible of ſo great a loſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1661" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1661.</head>
               <p>To put the Treaty of Peace in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution, and to determine the limits of our King's Conqueſts, the Sieurs <hi>Courtin</hi> Maſter of Requeſts, <hi>Talon</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendant of <hi>Artois,</hi> and <hi>Parmentier</hi> Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute to the Attorney-General, were
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:135098:49"/>
commiſſioned to treat with the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners of <hi>Spain, Vilteingh, Colins,</hi> and <hi>Anglanzey:</hi> They had laboured much in theſe particulars a long while, firſt at <hi>St. Omers,</hi> then at <hi>Arras,</hi> and laſtly they concluded happily at <hi>Metz,</hi> where they limited the Extents of <hi>Flanders, Artois, Hainault,</hi> and <hi>Lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>embourg;</hi> and having worthily acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted themſelves in their Employ, parted the 25th of <hi>November</hi> 1662.</p>
               <p>The Cardinal <hi>Mazarin</hi> did not long enjoy that Peace which he had procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to all <hi>France,</hi> having been almoſt ever ſince indiſpoſed. The Fire which in the beginning of <hi>February</hi> happened at the <hi>Louvre,</hi> and conſumed the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lery, of Pictures that look'd into the Garden, obliged his Eminence to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake his Bed, and retire to his own Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, where his diſeaſe continuing, he was adviſed to change the Air; which he did to <hi>Vincennes;</hi> but all this was not of force to prevent his death on the 9 of <hi>March</hi> following, to the great regret of the King, and all his Creatures.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:135098:50"/>But the following Marriages of the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> with the Princeſs of <hi>England,</hi> and the Prince of <hi>Florence</hi> with <hi>Mademoiſelle d'Orleans,</hi> cauſed the loſs of this great Miniſter to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt forgotten.</p>
               <p>The Sieur <hi>Fouquet,</hi> too intent on the encreaſe of his own Fortune, was ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſted at <hi>Nants</hi> the 5th of <hi>September,</hi> and conveyed to <hi>Vincennes,</hi> and from thence to the <hi>Baſtille.</hi> He was the firſt cauſe of the erection of the Chamber of Juſtice, which has been ſo advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous to thoſe people that deal in theſe affairs, by the detection of the waſting of the King's Revenues, which they have applied to their own private uſes, and to the great Purchaſes which they have made in the Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The extraordinary profuſion in the Conduct of this Miniſter, obliged the King to take ſome pains in the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his own Eſtate. We may ſay, that hereupon he effected two won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous things, and by which he ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed the Polititians. The admirable or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:135098:50"/>
and Oeconomy which he eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh'd in his own houſe, and the Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Diſcipline in his Armies; in all which particulars he raiſed the Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deur and Dignity of the Offices, and yet made as well the high as low Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers themſelves exactly ſubject to his own Authority and Power, who all remain at preſent in their perfect duty and dependance. The other thing is, his having made himſelf ſo abſolute a Maſter of all the Citadels and Fortreſſes of his Dominions, ſo that the Princes and Officers of the Crown, the Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours of Provinces, and of particular places, who heretofore made them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of too great value and conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, are now in a perfect obedience.</p>
               <p>He ſuppreſſed the Office of Super-Intendant of the Finances, and certain <note n="*">Officiers de l'E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpargue.</note> Officers in his Exchequer, and eſtabliſh'd a Council and Treaſury Royal, where nothing can be propoſed, nor one ſingle <hi>Sol</hi> paid out of his Coffers, unleſs it hath been there firſt reſolved and ordered. But
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:135098:51"/>
that which is moſt admirable, is, that his Majeſty does himſelf conſider and weigh all things, as well of great, as ſmall concern, whether far off or near, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary or ſuperfluous. His Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and Buildings at the <hi>Louvre, Tuil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leries,</hi> and other Houſes Royal, have found a place in that vaſt Spirit, amidſt the Citadels, and other important pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Kingdom. War, and affairs of State, have not abſolutely baniſh'd from his minde Pleaſure and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence: But having firſt heard the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious diſcourſes of the Mareſchal <hi>de Turenne,</hi> and the Sieur <hi>Colbert,</hi> he is pleaſed to confer with our Illuſtrious Artiſans, <hi>le Brun, le Nore,</hi> and all thoſe excellent Spirits who have the very genius and perfection of their ſeveral Arts.</p>
               <p>It ſeems about this time, <hi>Spain</hi> was minded to try whether his moſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Majeſty's new form of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would be maintained with force and vigour. To this purpoſe, the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron <hi>de Batteville</hi> paſt an affront on the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:135098:51"/>
                  <hi>Comte d'Eſtrade,</hi> at the entry of the <hi>Swede</hi>'s Embaſſador Extraordinary at <hi>London.</hi> And the <hi>Spaniards</hi> being the ſtronger, killed ſome <hi>French</hi> on the 10th of <hi>October.</hi> After this, perſwading the King of <hi>England</hi> that their Maſter had always acknowledged him, and aſſiſted againſt <hi>Cromwel,</hi> they endeavoured to draw him into the quarrel of his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Majeſty. Hereupon, our King complains at <hi>Madrid,</hi> and <hi>Bruxelles,</hi> and calls home his Commiſſioners, who were labouring with thoſe of <hi>Spain</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſettling the Limits of <hi>Flanders.</hi> In fine, <hi>France</hi> came off with honour in this action; and the Marquiſs <hi>de Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entes,</hi> Embaſſador extraordinary from <hi>Spain,</hi> made our King reparation, and aſſured him, that his Maſter had given order to all his Embaſſadors and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, to abſtain, and ſtrive no more with thoſe of <hi>France</hi> in all ſuch Ceremonies and publick actions where they both happen to aſſiſt. This was performed in the preſence of eight Embaſſadors and 22 Reſidents.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:135098:52"/>The Nativities of the <hi>Dauphin</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> and Prince of <hi>Spain,</hi> the firſt and ninth of <hi>November,</hi> was a new Bleſſing to both Nations. Oh what diſputes ſhall theſe Illuſtrious Compe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titors hereafter manage, to maintain the Grandeur and Glory of their Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors!</p>
               <p>The King reſolving a new promotion of Knights of both his Orders, a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Chapter was held at <hi>Fontainbleau</hi> about the end of <hi>December.</hi> Here, to the admiration of all men, the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi> demanded precedency of him of <hi>Vendôme, ſcïlt.</hi> the next place after the firſt Princes of the Blood; but in regard of thoſe Declarations, which <hi>Henry</hi> the great granted for the Duke of <hi>Vendôme</hi> the 15th of <hi>April</hi> 1610, Regiſtred in the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> the 30th of the ſame, the Duke of <hi>Longueville</hi>'s pretenſions were utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly defeated. The Princes of <hi>Vendôme</hi> having by their Legitimated birth, and in reſpect of Marriage, priority above all other Princes, and a power to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:135098:52"/>
to the Crown before the Dukes of <hi>Longueville;</hi> and all this is compri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſaid Declarations.</p>
               <p>On the 30th of <hi>December,</hi> the Novi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces marching before the ancient Knights, the ſix Eccleſiaſticks were firſt received into the quality of Commandeurs of the Order: After them, the 66 Knights Laicks. The King began with the Princes of <hi>Bourbon</hi> and <hi>Vendôme;</hi> but his Majeſty not able to comprehend the pretenſions of the <hi>Comte de Soiſſons,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> they were not received, ſaying, he would have them two go together, and march with the Dukes of <hi>Mercoeur,</hi> and <hi>Beaufort,</hi> who by right of Birth, and by the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Henry</hi> the Great, take place af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the <hi>Bourbons,</hi> and ought to precede the Princes of <hi>Courtenay,</hi> and <hi>Portugal,</hi> when they are acknowledged and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into this Quality. This was adjudged authentickly, and with great and mature conſideration of the Caſe, and executed in the preſence of the moſt Great and Auguſt Aſſembly of the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:135098:53"/>
Kingdom, and in the ſight of more than 100000 Witneſſes, all the people that were preſent at this ſo gallant action.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1662" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1662.</head>
               <p>The next day, being the firſt of <hi>Janu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ary,</hi> the grand Ceremony was continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at the <hi>Auguſtins,</hi> the Knights wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Collers of the Orders; and the ſecond, being apparelled in Mourning-Robes, they aſſiſt at a ſolemn Service for the Knights deceaſed; at which was a moſt magnificent Repreſentation; a King at Arms placed at the Head, and four Heralds at the Corners.</p>
               <p>And now it was that the <hi>Portugals</hi> had ſo well defended themſelves during this firſt Campagne, that the <hi>Spaniards</hi> were forced to begin a new War.</p>
               <p>On the 19th of <hi>January,</hi> the Carna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val begun with a Balet conſiſting of nine entries, at the <hi>Madame</hi>'s; in which, to render it the more excellent, was no omiſſion of coſt, or pleaſing objects. The grand Ball was danced the ſeventh
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:135098:53"/>
of <hi>February,</hi> where the Grandeur and glory of the Houſe of <hi>France</hi> was moſt lively repreſented, with the fifteen Alliances which ſhe had contracted in the Imperial Family.</p>
               <p>The Treaty with the Duke of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> in which he releaſed all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates to our King, under divers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, reſerving, however, to himſelf the Poſſeſſion, was verified the 27th of <hi>February.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>At this time the <hi>Portugals</hi> contracted a ſtrict Alliance with <hi>England,</hi> giving their <hi>Infanta, Tangier,</hi> and other ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantageous Conditions to <hi>Charles</hi> the ſecond, for his defence and aſſiſtance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> The Succours which they drew from thence, &amp; <hi>France,</hi> have eſtabliſh'd that Crown againſt all the efforts of his Catholick Majeſty.</p>
               <p>On the 27th of <hi>April,</hi> Peace, and a Renovation of the Alliance betwixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> was concluded and ſigned, after a Negotiation of eighteen Moneths.</p>
               <p>It was on the 18th of <hi>June</hi> following,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:135098:54"/>
that the famous Carrouſel, or Trium<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant Combat on Horſeback began. It was compoſed of five Squadrons or Companies. That of the King, were all apparrelled in the ancient Roman habit: That of the Duke of <hi>Orleans,</hi> repreſented <hi>Perſians;</hi> the Prince of <hi>Condé, Turks;</hi> the Duke of <hi>Enguien, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians;</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Guiſe,</hi> the <hi>Savages.</hi> The party of the Prince of <hi>Condé</hi> gain'd the Prize, and received a Diamond from the Queen-Mothers hand.</p>
               <p>The attempt late made at <hi>Rome,</hi> the 20th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> on the perſons of the Duke and Dutcheſs of <hi>Crequy,</hi> by the factions of the<note n="*">The Pope's Guards.</note> 
                  <hi>Corſes</hi> and <note n="*">Serjeants.</note> 
                  <hi>Sbirres,</hi> againſt the Law of Nations, and the cruel and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt perſecution rais'd againſt the <hi>French,</hi> cauſed the Duke <hi>Ceſarini,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Partiſans and friends of this Crown, to oblige the Embaſſador and his<note n="*">
                     <hi>L' Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadrice,</hi> in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal.</note> Lady to quit the City, and retire into the Eſtates of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> and ſo return into
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:135098:54"/>
                  <hi>France.</hi> The Church, and indeed all <hi>Europe</hi> found themſelves much ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lized at ſo ſoul an action, much bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Fauters and adherents of this capital Crime, which made ſo great a noiſe, and in the end was determined in a Treaty.</p>
               <p>The Marquiſs <hi>Mathei,</hi> a chief Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Plenipotentiary of his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Majeſty, was expell'd from his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, for having, unknown to him, and without his agreement, accepted the Office of Commander of his Holineſs's Arms.</p>
               <p>The Emperour and our King were at this time reconciled, by the mediation of the Marquiſs <hi>de la Fuente;</hi> the <hi>Comte Fuenſaldagne</hi> having laboured in that affair four years without effect. And their Majeſties gave mutual teſtimonies of affection and ſincerity, by ſeveral Letters which this Embaſſador exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the moneth of <hi>September.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Great joy appeared in <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> at the birth of <hi>Madame</hi> at the <hi>Louvre,</hi> the eighteenth of <hi>November.</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:135098:55"/>
This Princeſs was<note n="*">Ondoyée.</note> Chriſtened privately by the Cardinal <hi>Antoine,</hi> in preſence of the whole Court; and the 27th of <hi>December,</hi> the publick Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of her Baptiſm was performed by his Eminence, ſhe being named <hi>Anne-Elizabeth,</hi> by the Queen-Mother, and the Monſieur. She deceaſed the 30th following, and her Body was conveyed to <hi>St. Denis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About this time a Courier arrived to inform the King of the delivery of <hi>Dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kirk,</hi> the Fort of <hi>Mardike,</hi> and the greater and leſſer Fort of <hi>Bergue,</hi> and that his Troops were entred. Preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon this news, his Majeſty ſets out for the place, where he made his entry the ſecond of <hi>December,</hi> and returned again the ſixth, with the ſame diligence that at firſt he had taken the Voyage, accompanied with the Duke of <hi>Enguien</hi> and Duke of <hi>Beaufort;</hi> this laſt but lately landed from giving chaſe to the Pirates of <hi>Barbary.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This year was made happy in a concluſion of Marriage between the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:135098:55"/>
Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and Mademoiſelle <hi>de Valois.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Ballet of the Arts, conſiſting of ſeven Entries, was danced the firſt time at <hi>Madame's,</hi> where was preſent the Prince, Eldeſt ſon to the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1663" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1663.</head>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Crequy</hi>'s return into <hi>France,</hi> and the reduction of <hi>Benevento</hi> in the Eſtates Eccleſiaſtick, the 14th of <hi>March,</hi> into which place the Prince <hi>de la Ricca</hi> had retired, contrary to his word paſt to the Vice-roy of <hi>Naples,</hi> for having killed an Artiſan, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauched away his Wife, had much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmed the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> who through a panique fear, had made ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Levies, which again were disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded as ſuddainly: Which occaſioned a certain Cardinal to ſay,<note n="*">Qu'elle poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedoit la Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence des Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre-temps.</note> That they plaid at croſs purpoſes, having raiſed Arms, no-body knows againſt who, and laid
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:135098:56"/>
'em down again, not conſidering where they have made Peace.</p>
               <p>The Ceremony of the Nuptials of <hi>Mademoiſelle de Valois,</hi> and the <hi>Comte de Soiſſons</hi> Proxie to the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy,</hi> was performed at the <hi>Louvre</hi> the fourth of <hi>March,</hi> by the Cardinal <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toine:</hi> the ſeventh following, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs departed for <hi>Savoy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About the eighth of <hi>June, Dom John,</hi> who had promiſed to himſelf the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt of <hi>Portugal,</hi> was beaten in a ſet Battle at <hi>Evora,</hi> by the <hi>Comtes</hi> of <hi>Villa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flora,</hi> and <hi>Schomberg;</hi> recovering alſo at the ſame time, the ſaid Town, and all the other Conqueſts of that Prince du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the laſt Campagne.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Ottomans</hi> having formed a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne againſt the Empire, and being as yet in no very good condition to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taque it, propoſe an Accommodation. In the mean time, the <hi>Premier-Vizier,</hi> followed by 25000 Janizaries, 30000 <hi>Spahys,</hi> and 40000 men drawn out of <hi>Aſia,</hi> 15000 under the Baſſa of <hi>Boſnia,</hi> 14000 under him of <hi>Siliſtria,</hi> 8000
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:135098:56"/>
other Janizaries, and 12000 <hi>Spahys</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their General <hi>Ali-Baſſa,</hi> 6000 un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der him of <hi>Waradin,</hi> 9000 under <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel Abaffi,</hi> 12000 of <hi>Moldavia</hi> and <hi>Valachia,</hi> and 25000 who quartered neer the Grand Seignior's perſon at <hi>Andrinople,</hi> enters <hi>Belgrade</hi> the 18th of <hi>June,</hi> as a Conquerour; Beſieges and takes <hi>Neuhaſel</hi> the 27th of <hi>October;</hi> beſides that the vaſt body of ſuch an Army did ruine <hi>Nevutrade, Novitrade,</hi> and ſeveral other places.</p>
               <p>This year his Majeſty renewed the deſires of the deceaſed King, and his own, for the recovery of the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deries of the Order. And ſurely the Eſtates ought to be reſtored, after ſo much care and concern, which theſe two great Monarchs have ſhewed for that moſt lawful and juſt Reſtitution.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marſal</hi> was inveſted by the <hi>Comte de Guiche,</hi> the 17th of <hi>October:</hi> this Mareſchal had given order for the ſiege; but the King's arrival in eleven days, and the humble ſubmiſſion of Duke <hi>Charles,</hi> who reſtored the place to the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:135098:57"/>
perfect obedience of his Majeſty, fill'd the Court with joy; as alſo the Birth of a Prince of <hi>Tuſcany,</hi> the ninth of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> being returned into the <hi>Mediterranean</hi> Sea, continued his uſual courſe in performing many brave actions, and taking conſiderable Prizes; all which the King expected from his valour and courage.</p>
               <p>The Converſion of the Duke of <hi>Meklebourg,</hi> occaſioned the King to confer on him his Orders of Knighthood, and to do him ſeveral other publick Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, not uſual to any but Soveraign Princes: He is deſcended of the Kings of the <hi>Vandals,</hi> and from the <hi>Herules.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Embaſſadors from the <hi>Cantons</hi> of <hi>Swiſſerland,</hi> having been treated at <hi>Vincennes</hi> with a magnificence truly Royal, made their publick entry at <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris</hi> the ninth of <hi>November,</hi> with ſo great a ſplendor, that there was found more than 1000 Coaches in their Train. The eleventh following, they had Audience of the King, who took each of them by
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:135098:57"/>
the hand, and remained<note n="*">
                     <hi>Convert,</hi> but I ſuppoſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther uncover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</note> Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered during the Harangue of the firſt Embaſſador; to which his Majeſty anſwered with much joy and tenderneſs. The Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Renovation of the Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance was performed at <hi>Noſtre-Dame,</hi> where the Cardinal <hi>Antoine</hi> approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the place in which his Majeſty was then ſeated, and having placed the Book of the Goſpels before him, the King put his hand thereon with the Embaſſadors, while the Sieur <hi>d'Ormeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> read the Oath. After this, <hi>Te Deum</hi> was ſung, and the Cannon diſcharged.</p>
               <p>The Deputies of <hi>Avignon</hi> arriving to aſſure the King of the Fidelity and Zeal of that place, were preſented by the Sieur <hi>de Lyonne,</hi> and had Audience the 24th of <hi>November,</hi> in the Grand Cabinet.</p>
               <p>Not long after this, the Duke of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guien</hi> eſpouſed the Princeſs Palatine <hi>Anne</hi> of <hi>Bavaria.</hi> Their Majeſties were pleaſed to grace the Marriage-feaſt with their preſence: The Bridegroom-Duke
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:135098:58"/>
Duke dined at the Princeſs Palatine's his Mother-in-law, who regaled the Princes and Princeſſes with extream ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnificence. At Supper, the King and Queens were entertained at a Table of ſixty Diſhes, and ſix diſtinct Services, all nobly furniſhed.</p>
               <p>On the 14th of <hi>December,</hi> the King was pleaſed to declare in Parliament his pleaſure to beſtow the quality of Duke and Pair on fourteen perſons, whom he eſteemed moſt worthy of that Honour, as well by birth as merit; and theſe were, the Dukes of <hi>Vernüil, d'Eſtrées, de Gramont, de la Méleraye, de Maza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin, Villeroy, Mortemar, Crequy, Saint-Aignan, Foix, Liancour, Tremes, Noail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> and <hi>Coaſlin.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Articles of Marriage between the Emperour and the ſecond <hi>Infanta,</hi> having been publiſh'd the 18th of the inſtant <hi>December,</hi> the Contract was ſigned by the Count <hi>de Pelting,</hi> Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador for his Imperial Majeſty.</p>
               <p>The 27th of <hi>December,</hi> deceaſed at <hi>Turin Madame-Royale,</hi> much lamented
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:135098:58"/>
by her people, and the Court of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1664" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1664.</head>
               <p>With much diſpleaſure did <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> behold the death of the Dut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſs of <hi>Savoy,</hi> which happened on the 14th of <hi>January;</hi> and not long after, that of the Arch-Duke <hi>Charles-Joſeph</hi> the Emperour's Brother, to the no leſs ſorrow of <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt Repreſentation of the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let of <hi>Loves Diſguize,</hi> was performed the 13th of <hi>February,</hi> by a moſt delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome conteſt between <hi>Pallas</hi> attended by the Virtues and Arts, and <hi>Venus</hi> by the Graces and Pleaſures: to accommo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date the diſpute, <hi>Mercury</hi> directs them to the King, whoſe Arbitration they al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo deſire, and ſubmit to. Here the Scenes were ſo many and compleat, the fourteen Entries ſo ſplendid, the Habits ſo extream rich, the Speeches and Poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try ſo charming, the Dancers ſo grace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and exact, that in effect this grand
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:135098:59"/>
Divertiſement became moſt admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
               <p>And now our Troops appearing on their march in <hi>Modena,</hi> and <hi>Parma,</hi> the Marquiſs <hi>Mathei</hi> findes himſelf obliged to viſit that Frontier, and renew his Orders to his reformed Officers of thoſe Forces which he had lately raiſed. This alſo gave occaſion to revive the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences at <hi>Piſa,</hi> between the Sieur <hi>de Bourlemont</hi> Plenipotentiary for the King, and the Sieur <hi>Raſponi</hi> on the part of his Holineſs, which at laſt were happily ended by the Treaty of Peace concluded the 12th of <hi>February,</hi> where his Majeſty, the Dukes of <hi>Parma, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dena, Ceſarini,</hi> and the other Partiſans and Friends of <hi>France,</hi> received all ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction: It contained, among other things, that the <hi>Corſes</hi> were declared incapable to ſerve for the future in <hi>Rome,</hi> and the Eſtates Eccleſiaſtick: And that a Pyramide ſhould be erected directly oppoſite to their <hi>Corps-de-Garde,</hi> with an Inſcription containing the Decree againſt 'em. This War firſt
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:135098:59"/>
made known to the Court of <hi>France</hi> the perſons of the Cardinals <hi>d'Eſte, Maldachini,</hi> and <hi>Imperiale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third of <hi>March,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> parted from <hi>Toulon</hi> with ſeven Veſſels, to give chace to the Pirates of <hi>Barbary,</hi> who he had always defeated, and made Prize of, in many Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
               <p>The Peace of <hi>Italy</hi> obliged his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs to aſſiſt the Emperour with 2000 Horſe and 6000 Foot: And it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered at <hi>Ratisbone,</hi> that they march with diligence, in regard the <hi>Ottomans</hi> were incredible for number.</p>
               <p>The 7th of <hi>May,</hi> the King celebrates a great Feaſt at <hi>Verſaille,</hi> which laſted three days, under the Title of <hi>the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the Inchanted Iſland.</hi> It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with running at the Ring; and here the Marquiſs <hi>de la Valliere</hi> received the Prize. The ſecond day was repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a French Comedy, intermingled with Muſick, Poetry, and Entries of a Ballet: and the third a Ballet upon the Water, and artificial Fireworks.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:135098:60"/>The Cardinal <hi>Chiſi</hi> during this Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation in <hi>France,</hi> made choice of the Sieur <hi>Viſconti,</hi> Auditor of the <hi>Rota,</hi> for his <hi>Datary:</hi> the Sieur <hi>Bucinocorſi,</hi> Clerk of the Chamber, for his <hi>Major-domo:</hi> the Sieur <hi>Roberti,</hi> for his Secretary; and for his Protonotary, the Sieur <hi>Colonna</hi> ſon to the Prince <hi>de Carbognano.</hi> He was received the 12th of <hi>May</hi> at <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeilles,</hi> with extraordinary magnificence; the like through all the Kingdom, till he arrived <hi>incognito</hi> at <hi>Fountainbleau,</hi> where he was received by the King at the entrance into the Queen-Mothers Cabinet <hi>des Bains.</hi> Afterwards he made his publick entry at <hi>Fountain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleau</hi> the 18th of <hi>July,</hi> and at <hi>Paris</hi> the ninth of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> and returned to <hi>Rome</hi> with the ſame Pomp and magnificence that at firſt he arrived in <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Germany</hi> was at this time much A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmed at the raiſing the ſiege of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſe,</hi> and at the loſs of the Fort of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rin.</hi> The <hi>Primier Vizier</hi> had defeated the whole force of the Emperour's Army; and had it not been for the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:135098:60"/>
of the French Forces there, commanded by the <hi>Comte de Coligny,</hi> the Conſternation of that action had been extream. The <hi>Comte de la Fueillade</hi> ſignalized his valour on this occaſion, who arriving the 15th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feated more than 10000 <hi>Turks</hi> on the <hi>Raab,</hi> where they loſt 150 Colours, and ſixteen pieces of Cannon, which were planted on the other ſide of the River; and all this notwithſtanding the Groſs of their Army was not far diſtant. This great ſucceſs obliged the Turkiſh General to march towards <hi>Gran,</hi> there to joyn 20000 men, and thereby put himſelf in a condition to repair his ſaid loſs and ſhame, and alſo more effectually to ſecure that place, and <hi>Newhauſel.</hi> He call'd back alſo thoſe Troops which had already paſt the <hi>Vaag,</hi> to waſt the Countries of <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ravia,</hi> and <hi>Sileſia,</hi> in order to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of extending his Conqueſts to the very Walls of <hi>Vienna,</hi> and into the Hereditary Countries of the Emperour. But this Rout obliged a Truce between
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:135098:61"/>
the two Empires, and the Enemy to decamp the 29th of <hi>September.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Enterprize of <hi>Gigeri</hi> did not a little contribute to effect this; ſo alſo his Majeſties deſigne to render <hi>Africa</hi> and her Kings free and Chriſtian, and to eſtabliſh in that part of the World Commerce, and the Law of Nations. This had been truly a moſt Heroick action, and to the great profit of the whole World. It had had no doubt a favourable ſucceſs, had the generous reſolution of the Admiral Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> been followed. For the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorious are always obliged to fight and conquer; and they never take root in a ſtrange Country, otherwiſe than by continual Combats and Battles, which make 'em fear'd, and caſts the people into ſo great a conſternation, that in fine they are glad to ſubmit to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of their Conquerours.</p>
               <p>The Duke <hi>d'Oſſonne</hi> continuing the War in <hi>Portugal</hi> with no better ſucceſs than <hi>Dom John,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſtrive now to raiſe a more puiſſant Force than
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:135098:61"/>
ever, under the command of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſs <hi>de Caracene.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About this time the Engliſh offered ſeveral acts of Hoſtility to the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> and prepare for a War. The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament raiſe two Millions and a half of pounds ſterling to manage it; they do much damage on the Coaſt of <hi>Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi> and <hi>New-Holland;</hi> and their Fleet which ſcour'd the Seas, had order to ſee that no Engliſh were aboard any Dutch Veſſel; and if they found any, or if they refuſe to be ſearch'd, to fight 'em.</p>
               <p>The 16th of <hi>November,</hi> the Queen was delivered of the Princeſs <hi>Mary-Anne</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> who deceaſed the 26th of <hi>December.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This year the <hi>Venetians</hi> were at reſt, <hi>le Marquiſs Ville</hi> having viſited all the places of that State, and left 'em in good order.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Chevalier d'Hoquincourt</hi> with onely one Ship fought gloriouſly againſt 33 Turkiſh Gallies, ſunk five, and much indamaged the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:135098:62"/>The King deſirous that Juſtice ſhould be done in the moſt remote Provinces of his Kingdom, eſtabliſh'd a Chamber of Juſtice in <hi>Auvergne,</hi> where the Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent <hi>de Novion</hi> did well anſwer the choice which his Majeſty had made of ſo learned a perſon to preſide there on Grand days.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1665" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1665.</head>
               <p>The Ballet of the Birth of <hi>Venus</hi> was now danced: It was the Invention of the Dutcheſs of <hi>Orleans,</hi> to whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct his Majeſty had remitted the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of this affair. It conſiſted of two parts, both beginning with excellent Dialogues and Speeches. The firſt by <hi>Neptune</hi> and <hi>Thetis,</hi> and the ſecond by the <hi>Graces.</hi> It contained alſo twelve Majeſtick Entries; all which was aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with a Maſquerade of ten En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</p>
               <p>The Spaniſh Army now conſiſting of 10000 Horſe and 20000 Foot, that King refuſes the Mediation of the King
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:135098:62"/>
of <hi>England,</hi> as to a Peace with <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal;</hi> ſuppoſing the War with <hi>Holland</hi> would ſufficiently employ that Prince, and prevent his aſſiſting the ſaid King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> licenſe all private perſons to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quip out what Veſſels they can to cruze about, and do what miſchief they can to the Engliſh, whoſe Regiments they alſo caſheered, hoping thereby to repair the damage they ſuſtain by the rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Trade.</p>
               <p>The Admiralties on both ſides ſtrive who ſhall equip the moſt potent Navy, and prepare for a vigorous defence: The Engliſh having made Prize of 160 of their Veſſels. But that which ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized the whole World, was, that not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding this, they joyn'd their force againſt thoſe of <hi>Alger.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi>'s taking Arms, and the Intelligence he had with many Princes of <hi>Germany,</hi> obliged the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates of <hi>Weſtphalia</hi> to aſſemble, and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to ſtand upon their
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:135098:63"/>
guard. They alſo deſire the <hi>Hanſe</hi>-Towns at the ſame time not to furniſh themſelves with any Engliſh Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe; in like manner as his Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> had obliged them not to receive any out of <hi>Holland.</hi> And the better to defend themſelves, they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige <hi>Valdee</hi> and the <hi>Brunſwic</hi> Troops to ſecure their Frontiers.</p>
               <p>About this time, the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> laboured unſucceſsfully to match one of their Princeſſes to the Duke of <hi>Savoy,</hi> thereby to draw him off from our Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liance; on which condition they offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to joyn <hi>Alexandrin</hi> to his Eſtates, and ſeveral other advantages; which the Biſhop of <hi>Laon</hi> did not approve: He therefore demonſtrated to this Prince, that ſolid Goods are of far grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter conſideration than empty appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances; and that his Marriage with <hi>Made<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moiſelle de Nemours</hi> would ſettle his Eſtate and Houſe, which indeed ought never to be ſeparated from the Intereſts of <hi>France.</hi> He had before this taken much pains to conclude a three and
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:135098:63"/>
twentieth Alliance between the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Savoy</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> of the Duke of <hi>Nemours</hi> and <hi>Mademoiſelle de Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gueville.</hi> This Prince did what he could to diſ-engage himſelf, and procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſaid illuſtrious Prelate to be In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall'd Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Reims.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now it was that the King ſent into <hi>England</hi> the Duke of <hi>Verneüil,</hi> to endeavour a Reconciliation between his two neighbour-Nations, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent a cruel War. But they met the 13th of <hi>June;</hi> and Victory ſeemed doubtful for a while, till at laſt ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared in favour of the Duke of <hi>York;</hi> the <hi>Hollanders</hi> looſing their Admiral <hi>Opdam,</hi> and 17 ſhips.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time the King Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed a great Feaſt at <hi>Verſaille.</hi> After which, his Majeſty did proſcecute with much aſſiduity a former deſigne, to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite the two Seas by the Rivers of <hi>Guyenne</hi> and <hi>Languedoc.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Battle of <hi>Villa-vicioſa</hi> this year, did much abate the Ambition of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and no leſs raiſe the Courage of the <hi>Portugals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:135098:64"/>The Treaty of the King of <hi>England</hi> with the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter</hi> aſtoniſh'd the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> and the Troops ſent to their ſuccours, engaged us in a War with that Crown.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> took and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried off the ſhips in the Port of <hi>Bougie,</hi> in ſpite of all reſiſtance, from their Arms, Fire, or the Artillery of five Forts that commanded the place. He burnt the Admiral of <hi>Alger,</hi> and two other Veſſels, in the very mouth of the Harbour. Thoſe of <hi>Alger</hi> ſent out twenty ſhips to expel him out of their Road, he having onely four, two of which they perceived this Prince had taken from them. They were glad to uſe the advantage of the Night to fight him in: but they were reduced to the utmoſt Conſternation, when they per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived they got nothing but blows. In fine, they were ſo terrified, that they call'd back their Fleet again into their own Port. The 24th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> under <hi>Sarcelle,</hi> he encountered five Veſſels of <hi>Alger;</hi> and the order which he gave
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:135098:64"/>
for their deſtruction was ſo admirable, that in three hours he became Maſter of three; with the other two he continued fighting, when the Powder-room ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king fire, the Report was heard aſhore; and of this accident the Pirates made uſe, to fire the <hi>Saint Loüiſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By this time the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cruited, and were got to the mouth of the <hi>Thames,</hi> where they waited the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Engliſh Navy.</p>
               <p>On the 17th of <hi>September</hi> arrived the laſt hour of <hi>Philip</hi> the 4th of <hi>Spain,</hi> whoſe deceaſe was followed not long after by that of the Duke of <hi>Vandoſme</hi> the 22 of <hi>October.</hi> Their Majeſties and all the Court did atteſt their Sorrows to the Dutcheſs his Widow, and to the Duke of <hi>Mercoeur.</hi> To that end, the King ſent the Duke <hi>de Saint Agnan,</hi> apparell'd in a Mourning-Robe born up by two Gentlemen, the Corner'd Cap, and the Coller of the Order: the Ceremony was conducted by the King at Arms, and a Herald; who having preſented him with the Holy-Water,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:135098:65"/>
he caſt it three times on the Sepulchre of the deceaſed Prince, while his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty's Muſick ſing the <hi>De Profundis.</hi> The <hi>Comte de Sery</hi> performed the ſame Office on the part of <hi>Monſeigneur</hi> the <hi>Dauphin;</hi> and the <hi>Comte du Pleſſis-Praſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> and the Marquiſs <hi>de Pluvaut,</hi> for the Dukes of <hi>Orleans</hi> and <hi>Valois:</hi> which ended the Ceremony.</p>
               <p>The firſt of <hi>December,</hi> the Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chals <hi>du Pleſſis, d'Aumont,</hi> and <hi>de la Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>té-Seneterre,</hi> and the Marquiſs <hi>de Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tauſier,</hi> were received into the quality of Dukes and Pairs of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1666" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1666.</head>
               <p>The deceaſe of the Queen-Mother, which arrived the 20th of <hi>January,</hi> was moſt ſenſibly reſented by their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties and the whole Court. Not long after inſued a Rupture between <hi>France</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> in purſuance of the League Defenſive made by the Crown of <hi>France</hi> with the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> in the year 1662. And now his Majeſty by
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:135098:65"/>
his Declaration, publiſh'd his Intentions to relieve 'em, and joyn his Forces with theirs againſt the Engliſh, as well by Sea as Land.</p>
               <p>The Queen of <hi>Portugal,</hi> who had hitherto with ſo much glory and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity ſupported that Crown, deceaſed the 27th of <hi>February;</hi> at whoſe death the Court of <hi>Spain</hi> took no ſmall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, by their many Intrigues and Cabals which they rais'd afreſh in that Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The Biſhop of <hi>Munſter,</hi> who had ſo far terrified the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> as to occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion them to invoke the aid of <hi>France</hi> for their defence, about this time hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily concluded a Peace: this occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the return of our Troops. Thoſe of <hi>Holland</hi> have now, therefore, no more to do, than to proſecute their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine affairs, and minde their Wars with <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 29th of <hi>May,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> parted from <hi>Toulon</hi> with his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie's Fleet, on deſigne directly to meet a Squadron of the Engliſh,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:135098:66"/>
and fight 'em in aſſiſtance of the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers;</hi> and this they happily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, at the ſame time when our Troops by Land defended them from the Inſults of the Biſhop of <hi>Munſter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all the endeavours and Menaces of the <hi>Porte,</hi> the <hi>Vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> and the Marquiſs <hi>Ville,</hi> appeared this year the aggreſſors of a War, by Sea and by Land, in <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and in the Iſle of <hi>Candy,</hi> having beſieged <hi>New-Candy,</hi> and almoſt blockt up <hi>Canea.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Families of <hi>Vandoſme</hi> and <hi>d'E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrée</hi> received extraordinary joy at the Birth of a Prince of <hi>Savoy;</hi> they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been at no ſmall labour, and great expences, to prefer the Princeſſes of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours,</hi> and particularly the Queen of <hi>Portugal,</hi> the ornament and ſupport of that Crown. The aſſiſtance of <hi>France,</hi> and conduct of the Biſhop of <hi>Laon</hi> in this affair, hath defeated the Spaniſh deſignes in his intended Conqueſt of thoſe Dominions, which have now by this important Alliance taken faſt root, and re-eſtabliſh'd that ancient King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="123" facs="tcp:135098:66"/>The Fleets of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Holland</hi> being joyn'd the 11th of <hi>June,</hi> there followed a terrible Battle, and ſo reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute, that it continued till the 14th; at which time the Engliſh Ships retiring into the <hi>Thames,</hi> and ſoon recruiting with freſh men, they put out to Sea again, and another great fight began the fourth of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> which concluded to the equal prejudice of both parties. Several of the Engliſh purſuing their Enemies into the <hi>Vlie,</hi> fired there a great number of Merchants-ſhips. They had yet another Battle neer <hi>Calais,</hi> where the Engliſh having the Wind, and the Tempeſt being great, they run their Enemies on the adverſe Shore.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, the Duke of <hi>Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort</hi> having taken in the Squadron which had conducted the Queen to <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugal,</hi> ſail'd with intentions to joyn the <hi>Hollanders</hi> at <hi>Calais;</hi> but underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding they were retired, for fear to be alone expoſed to the Enemy, he gained <hi>Breſt</hi> in ſight of the Engliſh Fleet, they not able to prevent it; though in this
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:135098:67"/>
paſſage ſome of his ſhips being ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the reſt by a violent Tempeſt, the <hi>Triumph,</hi> the <hi>Mazarin,</hi> and the <hi>Ruby</hi> fell among the Engliſh, where valiantly fighting, they were much torn and ſhat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, and forc'd to retire into <hi>Havre,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the <hi>Ruby,</hi> who was ſo far engaged, that her Captain <hi>la Roche</hi> grapled with the Admiral of <hi>England,</hi> intending to pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh together, &amp; in fine obtained quarter.</p>
               <p>After the Alliance concluded, the 25th of <hi>October,</hi> between the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lector of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> and the Princes of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> certain Propoſitions of Accommodation were ſet afoot; His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain</hi> proteſting not to have made any act of Hoſtility a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt that Republick, complain'd that they had taken 200 Veſſels before ever the War broke out. And in order to aſſure Navigation, to re-eſtabliſh Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce, and procure a Peace, the States made known to his Majeſty, that it was neceſſary to appoint ſome place neu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tral, where to treat as well with them as their Allies.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:135098:67"/>The affair of <hi>Breme,</hi> which had ſo cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elly alarmed the Hanſe and Imperial Towns, was in fine determined the 25 of <hi>Nov.</hi> the <hi>Swedes</hi> contenting themſelves with the ſubmiſſion of the Inhabitants.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Valois</hi> was Baptized at the <hi>Palais Royal</hi> the ſixth of <hi>December,</hi> and held over the Font for the King of <hi>England,</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Enguien,</hi> who named him <hi>Philip-Charles;</hi> and by <hi>Mademoiſelle</hi> for the Queen. He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed the eighth enſuing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1667" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1667.</head>
               <p>The Queens happy delivery of a Princeſs, on the ſecond of <hi>January,</hi> was a joyful Newyears-gift to all <hi>France;</hi> and welcomed with the Ballet of the <hi>Muſes,</hi> adorn'd with many Entries, and Dialogues. This ſerved for a pleaſing Divertiſement all the Carnival; appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring always different, by reaſon of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinual new Embeliſhments and Scenes.</p>
               <p>The Grand Seigneur having now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved and diſpoſed all things neceſſary
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:135098:68"/>
for the important Siege of <hi>Candy,</hi> ſends the Grand Vizier to make the neceſſary preparations for the ſiege, and to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble in the Iſle 40000 men, and 15000 Pioneers; he held it in a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner inveſted round with Batteries and Attaques, in which he wrought from <hi>December,</hi> to the 27th of <hi>June,</hi> at which time it was beſieged with great vigour and reſolution, and extraordinarily well defended by the Marquiſs <hi>Ville,</hi> and thoſe Troops and Succours which the <hi>Venetians</hi> had ſent him.</p>
               <p>On the ſeventh of <hi>February,</hi> the Pope made a promotion of four Cardinals, the Duke of <hi>Vandôme,</hi> the Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Saltsburg,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate,</hi> and the Sieur <hi>Delphino;</hi> and names <hi>Roberti Spinola, Viſconti,</hi> and <hi>Caraccioli,</hi> who were reſerved <hi>in petto,</hi> ſince laſt year.</p>
               <p>The ſeveral Muſters of the King's Troops, and in particular, that of <hi>Oüil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> the Feaſts and Triumphs at <hi>Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſailles,</hi> and thoſe noble Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſements of running in<note n="*">Courſes de Quadrilles.</note> Squa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drons,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:135098:68"/>
and ſuch other delights, ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and their Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, who became perſwaded we paſt a whole Campagne thus.</p>
               <p>And now the War between <hi>England, France,</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi> growing towards an end, <hi>Breda</hi> is choſen for the place of Treaty; at which place the ſeveral De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties meeting, conclude a Peace the 31 of <hi>July.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the 20th of <hi>April,</hi> the King went perſonally to the Palace, to cauſe there to be verified his new Ordinance, by which he reforms and regulates Judicial proceedings.</p>
               <p>On the tenth of <hi>May</hi> deceaſed the Queen of <hi>Poland;</hi> and on the 22, Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the 7th, to whom ſucceeded <hi>Clement</hi> the 9th; both which have ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtained the Grandeur and Glory of the Church with much Majeſty.</p>
               <p>The Marriage of the Duke of <hi>Guiſe</hi> with <hi>Mademoiſelle d'Alençon,</hi> was ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebrated the 15th of <hi>May.</hi> The next day, the Court departed to put the Queen in poſſeſſion of her Rights late
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:135098:69"/>
fallen to her in the <hi>Low-Countries:</hi> the reaſons of which are publick, &amp; in Print. The march of our Armies gave the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larm to <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Holland;</hi> and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged the Marquiſs <hi>de Caſtel-Rodrigo</hi> to demoliſh ſeveral places that wanted ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Forces to defend 'em. We be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun at <hi>Armentiers;</hi> and his Majeſty ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving paſt as far as <hi>Charles-Roy,</hi> cauſed the Fortifications to be repaired.</p>
               <p>After this, he forces <hi>Tournay</hi> to ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render the 24th of <hi>June,</hi> and <hi>Doüay</hi> the ſixth of <hi>July.</hi> On <hi>Dunkirk</hi>-ſide, the Mareſchal <hi>D'Aumont</hi> with another Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my takes <hi>Bergue</hi> and <hi>Furne,</hi> and inveſts <hi>L'iſle,</hi> where the Siege was carried on with much vigour, his Majeſty being always in action, and going the Rounds continually. This Town was taken after a Siege of ſeventeen daies, and nine from the firſt opening the Trenches. The <hi>Comte de Broüay,</hi> who demanded four daies, was much ſurpriſed to finde the King anſwer with a denial, and within three hours after force the place to ſurrender.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:135098:69"/>This propoſition from that Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour obliged our Monarch to lie that night at <hi>Arlebec.</hi> He ordered the <hi>Comte</hi> of <hi>Liſlebonne</hi> to march with the <hi>Lorain</hi> Forces, and joyn the Marquiſs <hi>de Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quy,</hi> and <hi>Bellefonds,</hi> and then to meet the Enemy; which they did ſo happily as to defeat the Prince <hi>de Ligne,</hi> and the <hi>Comte de Marcin;</hi> which ſtaggered all <hi>Flanders.</hi> His Majeſty was ready to aſſiſt, and remained about a quarter of a League from <hi>Gand,</hi> ſleeping in his Coach that night at the head of the Bridge over the River of <hi>Bruges,</hi> to back and aſſiſt his Army in caſe of oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion.</p>
               <p>The Town and Citadel of <hi>Courtray</hi> was alſo taken, with <hi>Oudenarde</hi> and <hi>Aloſt;</hi> which being retaken by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy, was ſoon after recovered again by the Mareſchal <hi>de Camp</hi> General, and demoliſh'd.</p>
               <p>The Empreſs being delivered of an Arch-Duke, their Majeſties ſent the Marquiſs <hi>de Guitry</hi> to congratulate the Court of <hi>Vienna,</hi> who notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:135098:70"/>
enjoy'd not long that happineſs.</p>
               <p>The Eſtates and People of <hi>Portugal</hi> about this time forced their King to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the Government, which they conferred on <hi>D. Pedro</hi> his Brother; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo Commiſſaries are appointed to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the complaints of the Queen, as to a Nullity of Marriage.</p>
               <p>The Divertiſements of <hi>Shrovetide</hi> began with a Maſquerade, call'd the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naval,</hi> conſiſting onely of ſeven Entries. The firſt overture was performed by a Speech; but the Dialogue between <hi>Carnaval</hi> and <hi>Gallantry,</hi> with an admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Conſort of Muſick, gave wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful ſatisfaction to the Spectators.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1668" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1668.</head>
               <p>On the 21th of <hi>January, Madame</hi> was Baptized at the <hi>Tuilleries,</hi> and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by the Dutcheſs Dowager of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leans</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Enguien, Maria-Thereſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame day was the Cardinal Duke of <hi>Vandôme</hi> conducted to have Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:135098:70"/>
from their Majeſties, by the Sieur <hi>de Saintot</hi> Maſter of the Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies, with a very great Train. The King having deſired the Pope to be Godfather to Monſeigneur the <hi>Dauphin,</hi> the news appeared moſt agreable to his Holineſs, who therefore prefer'd this Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Cardinal to thoſe of his own Bloud, and Princes extreamly dear to him; conferring on him to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, with much joy, his Power and Authority, and that of the Holy Seat; which in truth he managed and ſuſtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with great Honour; giving the King to underſtand that it belonged to his Holineſs, repreſented in his perſon, to Name the Prince <hi>Dauphin;</hi> and to the Biſhops of <hi>France</hi> to pay to the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Seat, and to his dignity, all due re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects and ſubmiſſions. In fine, the <hi>Dauphin</hi> was named <hi>Lewis,</hi> and the Ceremony performed at <hi>St. Germains</hi> the 24th of <hi>March.</hi> The Baptiſmal Honours were carried by the <hi>Bourbons,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Vandôme</hi> bore up the Train of the Prince's Mantle-Royal,
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:135098:71"/>
taking place immediately after the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of the Bloud.</p>
               <p>The Diſpenſation which Monſieur the Legat granted for a ſecond Marriage of the Queen of <hi>Portugal</hi> with that Prince, was an extraordinary piece of State, and good Fortune. <hi>France</hi> and that Crown have as much cauſe to praiſe the Conduct of that action, as the Council of <hi>Spain</hi> juſt occaſion to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear troubled, who under colour of gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to that Prince a Daughter of the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> would by that means, very ſubtilly, have made themſelves Maſters of that Kingdom.</p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> and the <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valier de Vandôme</hi> in the thirteenth year of his age, embarqued themſelves with intentions to make a deſcent into <hi>Spain;</hi> but the enſuing Peace, and a violent Tempeſt concurring, put a ſtop to the deſignes of our great Admiral; who notwithſtanding could not but ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire the aſſurance and courage of this young Prince.</p>
               <p>At the ſame time, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehending
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:135098:71"/>
ſome fears from the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of the King's Arms into their neighbourhood, and forgetting all the benefits they have received from <hi>France,</hi> endeavour with too much heat and precipitation a League Defenſive with all the Potentates of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King's Voyage into the <hi>Franche-Comte,</hi> and Conqueſt of that Province during the Carnaval, was a great a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the moſt glorious Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prize that any Prince could poſſibly perform in leſs than 15 days.</p>
               <p>The bare name and reputation of the Arms of this Monarch, forced <hi>Spain,</hi> formerly reſolved never to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> to conclude a Peace with him, and renounce the name and Arms of that Crown, the 25 of <hi>February.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The meeting for Peace between the two Crowns of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing appointed at <hi>Aix-la-Chapelle,</hi> the Treaty was concluded and ſigned the ſecond of <hi>April,</hi> though with a ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble regret from the French Army and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:135098:72"/>
Nation, who deſired nothing more, than a continuance of War with the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards.</hi> But it was at the requeſt of <hi>Clement</hi> the 9th, that the King did yield to a ſuſpention of Arms during the moneth of <hi>April</hi> and <hi>May,</hi> in which he did more conſider the good of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, than the Grandeur and Glory of his own perſon and Eſtates. By this Treaty his Majeſty kept his Conqueſts of the year paſt, leaving to <hi>Spain</hi> that of the <hi>Franche Comte.</hi> This great Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch, herein, ſacrifizing one of the bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt Conqueſts that ever ſhall be, to the repoſe of his Subjects; and this it was which he procured them in all his Rencounters.</p>
               <p>The Alliances which ſoon after were concluded between the Dukes <hi>Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milian</hi> of <hi>Bavaria</hi> Brother to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, and <hi>Mademoiſelle de Boüillon,</hi> and <hi>John Frederic de Brunſwic-Lunebourg</hi> Married to the Princeſs <hi>Benedicta Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine de Bavaria,</hi> were of no ſmall glory to <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Eſtates of <hi>Portugal</hi> now preſs
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:135098:72"/>
                  <hi>Dom Pedro</hi> to receive the Title of King on the Abdication of his Brother <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſo;</hi> but not able to perſwade him to that, they extend his power equal to that of Royalty, and in ſuch condition he treats with all the Potentates of the World.</p>
               <p>The King ſeeking all occaſions to oblige his Holineſs and the Holy Sea, makes it his own requeſt to demoliſh the Piramide heretofore erected againſt the <hi>Corſes,</hi> by the Treaty of <hi>Piſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Marquiſs <hi>de Crequy, de Belleſons,</hi> and <hi>d'Humieres,</hi> were created Mareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chals of <hi>France.</hi> And on the 19th of <hi>July</hi> was performed an extraordinary magnificence at <hi>Verſailles.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Great Honour was acquired by the Marquiſs <hi>Ville</hi> in the defence of <hi>Candy,</hi> the Marquiſs <hi>de Saint André-Montbrun</hi> ſharing with him the Glory of that Action. Theſe two gallant men have ſo ſignalized their valour in this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Expedition, that they have rendred their names Immortal.</p>
               <p>The Nativity of the Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:135098:73"/>
on the 5th of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> occaſioned much joy to the Court of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ill Intelligence between the Queen of <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Dom John,</hi> begun ſoon after the Peace; the occaſion, that Prince's refuſal to paſs into <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> he reſolving to ſtay at Court as an obſtacle to the Fortunes of Father <hi>Nitard.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The King judging the Letter circu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary of the four Biſhops, ſent about to all the others to unite them in reſiſting the Execution of the Pope's <hi>Breve</hi> which had named ſeveral Prelates to proceed againſt thoſe four, to be an ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular action; did, by his Arreſt in Council, and by the interpoſition of the Biſhop Duke of <hi>Laon,</hi> calm and aſſwage the greateſt Storm which the Church of <hi>France</hi> had perhaps ever ſeen, rais'd through the Vertues and Merits of ſome rare Spirits, who with ſo much heat and obſtinacy did oppoſe the Book of <hi>Janſenius;</hi> from which ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching troubles this Illuſtrious Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late found the way to diſ-engage them,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:135098:73"/>
with that ſweetneſs and prudence wherewith he managed all things, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printing in their Hearts, at the ſame time, profound Sentiments of reſpect and ſubmiſſion for the Holy Sea.</p>
               <p>By vertue of the Emperour's Mandate brought by the Marquiſs <hi>de Bade,</hi> the Electour Palatine, on the 14th of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember,</hi> cauſed to be publiſh'd a Suſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Arms, and Ceſſation of acts, of Hoſtility between him and the Duke of <hi>Lorain.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1669" type="year">
               <head>
                  <hi>Anno</hi> 1669.</head>
               <p>The <hi>Portugals</hi> were overjoy'd at the Birth of the <hi>Infanta</hi> of <hi>Portugal,</hi> which arrived the ſixth of <hi>January.</hi> This Princeſs was named by the Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of <hi>France,</hi> after her Majeſty, <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth-Maria Loüiſa.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Empreſs alſo was delivered of a Daughter the 18th following.</p>
               <p>About the end of this moneth, the Elector Palatine, and the Duke of <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain,</hi> were obliged to disband their
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:135098:74"/>
Forces, to which his Majeſtie's Arms under the command of the Mareſchal <hi>de Crequy</hi> had compell'd 'em.</p>
               <p>And now it was that his Holineſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited all Chriſtian Princes to ſuccour <hi>Candy,</hi> and to which he applied his ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt, as alſo to pacifie the Kingdom of <hi>Poland.</hi> He ſent alſo a <hi>Breve</hi> to <hi>Lisbon</hi> in confirmation of that Queens Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to <hi>Dom Pedro.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>About this time, the Council of <hi>Spain</hi> reſolved, and took ſome pains to raiſe a Regiment of Guards, to be always neer the perſon of his Catholick Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty. This Novelty was nothing plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to the Nobleſs and people; it was alſo one pretence of the diſcontent of <hi>Dom John.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This <hi>Shrovetide</hi> was preſented the Ballet of <hi>Flora,</hi> compoſed of fifteen Majeſtick Entries. <hi>Winter</hi> made the Overture with a handſome Speech; the <hi>Sun,</hi> who expell'd him, chang'd the face of the Theater into a ſmiling Campagne. This Glorious Planet accompanied with the Elements made the firſt Entry. All
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:135098:74"/>
the other parts were correſpondent to this magnifique Spectacle; where the beauty of the Machines, the richneſs of the Habits, and the Charms of the La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies did not a little contribute to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this Piece into the number of the moſt glorious.</p>
               <p>On the firſt of <hi>February,</hi> the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of the Empire, <hi>Spain, England, Swede,</hi> and the States, concluded at the <hi>Hague</hi> the Treaty of triple Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; the <hi>Swedes</hi> being to receive of his Catholick Majeſty nine hundred thouſand Livres.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of the Spring, the Duke of <hi>Beaufort,</hi> and the <hi>Chevalier de Vandôme</hi> departed for <hi>Toulon,</hi> there to haſten the Succours deſigned for <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Duke of <hi>Anjou</hi> was Baptized the fourth of <hi>March,</hi> and named <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> by the Duke of <hi>Orleans</hi> and <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dame,</hi> repreſenting the Emperour and Queen of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Admiral Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived from the Pope a <hi>Breve,</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:135098:75"/>
him General of the Troops Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtick, going for <hi>Candy,</hi> to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in the abſence of <hi>Dom Vincenzo Roſpiglioſi.</hi> His Holineſs having ſent him the Standard of the Holy Sea.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Portugal</hi> demanding to go into the Iſle of <hi>Terceres,</hi> he was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy'd thither in the beginning of <hi>May,</hi> by the <hi>Comte de Prado.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dom John,</hi> about this time, made no unhappy Agreement. He quitted <hi>Spain</hi> to Father <hi>Nitard,</hi> reſerving to himſelf the Title of perpetual Governour of the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> with the Vice-Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and Vicariat-General of <hi>Arragon, Valancia,</hi> and <hi>Catalonia;</hi> with power to provide to all Offices and Benefices in the ſaid places.</p>
               <p>Prince <hi>Charles</hi> of <hi>Lorain,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Newbourg,</hi> remain now the onely pretenders to the Crown of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> Their Partiſans take Arms, and urge that affair to ſo great an extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that they open the Eyes of the <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonois;</hi> and the Prince <hi>Wieſnowiski</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing propoſed to their election, he was
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:135098:75"/>
univerſally received: and thus he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily aſcended the Throne of his own Nation, and of his Fathers, the 19th of <hi>June.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our Army having paſt from <hi>Toulon</hi> to <hi>Candy</hi> in fourteen daies, that place being now extreamly preſt, and a fair occaſion to charge the Enemy preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it ſelf, Monſieur <hi>de Navailles</hi> ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lied with the Army. The Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> would aſſiſt with his own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal valour and courage in ſo brave an Enterprize. The <hi>Chevalier de Vandôme</hi> ſhewed there his great Heart and reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution, and that he was an accompliſht Souldier and Captain. The Admiral having landed eighteen hundred men from Shipboard, beat the <hi>Turks</hi> out of their Trenches; and no doubt we had raiſed the Siege, had not a panique fear frighted our men from ſo promiſing a Victory. The <hi>Chevalier</hi> call'd to ſeveral Officers by their Names; but ineffectually. Fortune, with much happineſs, and ſome difficulty, brought off this young <hi>Mars</hi> from the Embar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:135098:76"/>
of this ſad Retreat. But the Duke of <hi>Beaufort</hi> remain'd in the Field of Battle, which he had won, and which indeed he could never be made to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandon, being there either ſlain or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by the <hi>Ottomans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe many great Services which the Cardinal Duke of <hi>Vandôme</hi> had rendered to the King and State, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded with the pains he took to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance the Succours for <hi>Candy.</hi> His Death arrived the ſixth of <hi>Auguſt;</hi> a loſs for which the Courts of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>France</hi> and all <hi>Provence</hi> were not eaſily comforted.</p>
               <p>The Dutcheſs of <hi>Vondôme,</hi> who had been a perfect Example and Model of Vertue and Piety, and the Queen of <hi>England</hi> youngeſt Daughter of <hi>Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the great, deceaſed the 8th, and the 10th of <hi>September.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And now it was that the Prince of <hi>Tuſcany</hi> finiſh'd his Voyage of <hi>Europe,</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> avowing that he had not ſeen a fairer Country than <hi>France,</hi> nor a more admirable <hi>Heros</hi> than her King.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:135098:76"/>To conclude the Events of this year, King <hi>Cazimir,</hi> after he had ſeen another King Elected into his place, quitted <hi>Poland,</hi> and arrived in <hi>France,</hi> where he was moſt ſplendidly regaled at <hi>Chantilly</hi> by Monſieur the Prince, and Monſieur the Duke.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:135098:77"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:135098:77" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
